<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
  or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
  distributed with this work for additional information
  regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
  to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
  "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
  with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
  software distributed under the License is distributed on an
  "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
  KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
  specific language governing permissions and limitations
  under the License.    
-->
<document>

 <properties>
  <title>Apache James Server 3 - Configuring the POP3 Service</title>
 </properties>

<body>

  <section name="POP3 Configuration">
  
    <p>Consult <a href="https://github.com/apache/james-project/tree/master/server/apps/spring-app/src/main/resources/pop3server.xml">pop3server.xml</a> in GIT to get some examples and hints.</p>

    <p>The POP3 service is controlled by a configuration block in the pop3server.xml.
       The pop3server tag defines the boundaries of the configuration block.  It encloses 
       all the relevant configuration for the POP3 server.  The behavior of the POP service is
       controlled by the attributes and children of this tag.</p>
    
    <p>This tag has an optional boolean attribute - <strong>enabled</strong> - that defines whether the service is active or not.  The value defaults to "true" if
       not present.</p>
    
    <p>The standard children of the pop3server tag are:</p>

      <dl>
        <dt><strong>bind</strong></dt>
        <dd>Configure this to bind to a specific inetaddress. This is an optional integer value.  This value is the port on which this POP3 server is configured 
      to listen. If the tag or value is absent then the service 
      will bind to all network interfaces for the machine If the tag or value is omitted, the value will default to the standard POP3 port, 11
    port 995 is the well-known/IANA registered port for POP3S  ie over SSL/TLS 
    port 110 is the well-known/IANA registered port for Standard POP3</dd>
        <dt><strong>connectionBacklog</strong></dt>
        <dd></dd>
        <dt><strong>tls</strong></dt>
        <dd>Set to true to support STARTTLS or SSL for the Socket.
         To use this you need to copy sunjce_provider.jar to /path/james/lib directory. To create a new keystore execute:
             keytool -genkey -alias james -keyalg RSA -storetype PKCS12 -keystore /path/to/james/conf/keystore<br/>
            Please note that each POP3 server exposed on different port can specify its own keystore, independently from any other
            TLS based protocols.</dd>
        <dt><strong>handler.helloName</strong></dt>
        <dd>This is the name used by the server to identify itself in the POP3 
        protocol.  If autodetect is TRUE, the server will discover its 
        own host name and use that in the protocol.  If discovery fails, 
        the value of 'localhost' is used.  If autodetect is FALSE, James 
        will use the specified value.</dd>
        <dt><strong>handler.connectiontimeout</strong></dt>
        <dd>Connection timeout in secconds</dd>
        <dt><strong>handler.connectionLimit</strong></dt>
        <dd>Set the maximum simultaneous incoming connections for this service</dd>
        <dt><strong>handler.connectionLimitPerIP</strong></dt>
        <dd>Set the maximum simultaneous incoming connections per IP for this service</dd>
        <dt><strong>handler.handlerchain</strong></dt>
        <dd>This loads the core CommandHandlers. Only remove this if you really 
             know what you are doing</dd>
        <dt><strong>bossWorkerCount</strong></dt>
        <dd>Set the maximum count of boss threads. Boss threads are responsible for accepting incoming POP3 connections
              and initializing associated resources. Optional integer, by default, boss threads are not used and this responsibility is being dealt with
              by IO threads</dd>

        <dt><strong>ioWorkerCount</strong></dt>
        <dd>Set the maximum count of IO threads. IO threads are responsible for receiving incoming POP3 messages and framing them
              (split line by line). IO threads also take care of compression and SSL encryption. Their tasks are short-lived and non-blocking.
              Optional integer, defaults to 2 times the count of CPUs.</dd>

        <dt><strong>maxExecutorCount</strong></dt>
        <dd>Set the maximum count of worker threads. Worker threads takes care of potentially blocking tasks like executing POP3 requests.
            Optional integer, defaults to 16.</dd>


          <dt><strong>useEpoll</strong></dt>
          <dd>true or false - If true uses native EPOLL implementation for Netty otherwise uses NIO. Defaults to false.</dd>

          <dt><strong>gracefulShutdown</strong></dt>
          <dd>true or false - If true attemps a graceful shutdown, which is safer but can take time. Defaults to true.</dd>
      </dl>

  </section>

</body>

</document>

