<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
  or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
  distributed with this work for additional information
  regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
  to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
  "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
  with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
  software distributed under the License is distributed on an
  "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
  KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
  specific language governing permissions and limitations
  under the License.
-->
<document>

    <properties>
        <title>Apache James Server 3 - JMAP Configuration</title>
    </properties>

    <body>

        <section name="JMAP configuration">

            <p><a href="https://jmap.io/">JMAP</a>  is intended to be a new standard for email clients to connect to mail
                stores. It therefore intends to primarily replace IMAP + SMTP submission. It is also designed to be more
                generic. It does not replace MTA-to-MTA SMTP transmission.</p>

            <p>Cassandra Guice proposes a JMAP implementation.</p>

            <subsection name="jmap.properties">

                <p>Consult <a href="https://github.com/apache/james-project/blob/master/dockerfiles/run/guice/cassandra/destination/conf/jmap.properties">jmap.properties</a> in GIT to get some examples and hints.</p>

                <br/>

                <dl>
                    <dt><strong>enabled</strong></dt>
                    <dd>true/false. Governs whether JMAP should be enabled</dd>

                    <dt><strong>jmap.port</strong></dt>
                    <dd>Optional. Defaults to 80. The port this server will be listening on. This value must be a valid
                    port, ranging between 1 and 65535 (inclusive)</dd>

                    <dt><strong>tls.keystoreURL</strong></dt>
                    <dd>Keystore to be used for generating authentication tokens for password authentication mechanism.
                    This should not be the same keystore than the ones used by TLS based protocols.</dd>

                    <dt><strong>tls.secret</strong></dt>
                    <dd>Password used to read the keystore</dd>

                    <dt><strong>jwt.publickeypem.url</strong></dt>
                    <dd>Optional. JWT tokens allows request to bypass authentication</dd>

                    <dt><strong>url.prefix</strong></dt>
                    <dd>Optional. Configuration urlPrefix for JMAP routes.</dd>
                    <dd>Default value: http://localhost.</dd>

                    <dt><strong>upload.max.size</strong></dt>
                    <dd>Optional. Configuration max size Upload in new JMAP-RFC-8621.</dd>
                    <dd>Default value: 30M. Supported units are B (bytes) K (KB) M (MB) G (GB).</dd>

                    <dt><strong>view.email.query.enabled</strong></dt>
                    <dd>Optional boolean. Defaults to false.</dd>
                    <dd>Should simple Email/query be resolved against a Cassandra projection, or should we resolve them against ElasticSearch?
                        This enables a higher resilience, but the projection needs to be correctly populated.</dd>

                    <dt><strong>jmap.version.default</strong></dt>
                    <dd>Optional string. Defaults to draft. Allowed values: draft, rfc-8621.</dd>
                    <dd>Which version of the JMAP protocol should be served when none supplied in the Accept header.
                    Defaults to draft for legacy reasons (avoid breaking changes) but setting the value to
                    rfc-8621 allow compatibility with other third party apps.</dd>
                </dl>

            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Wire tapping">
                <p>Enabling <b>TRACE</b> on <b>org.apache.james.jmap.wire</b> enables reactor-netty wiretap, logging of
                all incoming and outgoing requests, outgoing requests. This will log also potentially sensible information
                like authentication credentials.</p>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="JMAP-draft vs JMAP-RFC-8621">
                <p>James had been supporting an implementation based on an early specification of JMAP, what we call here
                <em>JMAP-draft</em> version. But the protocol went under a lot of changes until its finalization as an
                official RFC.</p>

                <p>The finalized version of JMAP regarding the core specifications [<a href="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc8620">RFC-8620</a>]
                and the mail specifications [<a href="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc8621">RFC-8621</a>] are being
                currently implemented in James (<em>JMAP-RFC-8621</em> version). It's supposed to replace at term the
                <em>JMAP-draft</em> version.</p>

                <p>Meanwhile, both versions will be available. The version by default will be <em>JMAP-draft</em> during
                the time it takes to implement the new version. If you want to use a specific version for a request,
                you will need to add an extra <em>jmapVersion</em> field in your <b>Accept</b> header of your JMAP request:</p>

                <ul>
                    <li><b>JMAP-draft</b>: <em>Accept: application/json; jmapVersion=draft</em></li>
                    <li><b>JMAP-RFC-8621</b>: <em>Accept: application/json; jmapVersion=rfc-8621</em></li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Annotated specification">
                <p>The <a href="https://github.com/apache/james-project/tree/master/server/protocols/jmap-rfc-8621/doc/specs/spec">annotated documentation</a>
                presents the limits of the JMAP RFC-8621 implementation part of the Apache James project.</p>

                <p>Some methods / types are not yet implemented, some implementations are naive, and the PUSH is not supported yet.</p>

                <p>Users are invited to read these limitations before using actively the JMAP RFC-8621 implementation, and should ensure their
                client applications only uses supported operations.</p>

                <p>Contributions enhancing support are furthermore welcomed.</p>

                <ul>The list of tested JMAP clients are:
                    <li><a href="https://open-paas.org/">OpenPaaS</a> is actively using the draft version of the JMAP implementation. Migration to
                    RFC-8621 is planned.</li>
                    <li>Experiments had been run on top of <a href="https://github.com/iNPUTmice/lttrs-android">LTT.RS</a>. Version in the Accept
                        headers needs to be explicitly set to `rfc-8621`. <a href="https://github.com/linagora/james-project/pull/4089">Read more</a>.</li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>
        </section>

    </body>

</document>
