<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
  or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
  distributed with this work for additional information
  regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
  to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
  "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
  with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
  software distributed under the License is distributed on an
  "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
  KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
  specific language governing permissions and limitations
  under the License.    
-->
<document>

 <properties>
  <title>Apache James Server 3 - Cassandra Configuration</title>
 </properties>

<body>

  <section name="Cassandra Configuration">

    Note: Cassandra is only available with Guice wiring (cassandra-guice and cassandra-guice-ldap).

    <p>Consult <a href="https://github.com/apache/james-project/blob/master/dockerfiles/run/guice/cassandra/destination/conf/cassandra.properties">cassandra-template.properties</a> to get some examples and hints.</p>

      <dl>
        <dt><strong>cassandra.nodes</strong></dt>
        <dd>List of some nodes of the cassandra's cluster in following format host:port or host, if the port is not specified we use 9042</dd>

        <dt><strong>cassandra.keyspace</strong></dt>
        <dd>Is the name of the keyspace used by James.</dd>

        <dt><strong>cassandra.replication.factor</strong></dt>
        <dd>Is the replication factor. (should be 1, as cluster is not yet supported)</dd>

        <dt><strong>cassandra.query.logger.constant.threshold</strong></dt>
        <dd>Optional.
        If specified all queries that take more than the given integer in millisecond will be considered slow and logged.
          If not specified by default a DynamicThresholdQueryLogger will be used (see above)</dd>

        <dt><strong>cassandra.query.slow.query.latency.threshold.percentile</strong></dt>
        <dd>Default is com.datastax.driver.core.QueryLogger.DEFAULT_SLOW_QUERY_THRESHOLD_PERCENTILE.
        The latency percentile beyond which queries are considered 'slow' and will be logged.
          If you specify cassandra.query.logger.constant.threshold, you should not specify this property</dd>

        <dt><strong>cassandra.query.logger.max.query.string.length</strong></dt>
        <dd>Default is com.datastax.driver.core.QueryLogger.DEFAULT_MAX_QUERY_STRING.LENGTH.
          The maximum length of a CQL query string that can be logged verbatim by the cassandra driver</dd>

        <dt><strong>cassandra.query.logger.max.logged.parameters</strong></dt>
        <dd>Default is com.datastax.driver.core.QueryLogger.DEFAULT_MAX_LOGGED_PARAMETERS.
          The maximum number of query parameters that can be logged by the cassandra driver</dd>

        <dt><strong>cassandra.query.logger.max.parameter.value.length</strong></dt>
        <dd>Default is com.datastax.driver.core.QueryLogger.DEFAULT_MAX_PARAMETER_VALUE_LENGTH.
          The maximum length of query parameter value that can be logged by the cassandra driver</dd>

        <dt><strong>cassandra.readTimeoutMillis</strong></dt>
        <dd>Optional.
          If specified defines the Cassandra <a href="http://docs.datastax.com/en/developer/java-driver/2.1/manual/socket_options/">driver read timeout</a></dd>

        # Read com.datastax.driver.core.PoolingOptions for knowing defaults value
        # No value here will default to driver's default value

        # cassandra.pooling.local.max.connections=8
        # cassandra.pooling.local.max.requests=128
        ## In ms. Should be higher than socket read timeout
        # cassandra.pooling.timeout=5000
        ## In seconds.
        # cassandra.pooling.heartbeat.timeout=30

        <dt><strong>cassandra.pooling.local.max.connections</strong></dt>
        <dd>Optional.
          If specified defines the Cassandra <a href="http://docs.datastax.com/en/developer/java-driver/2.1/manual/pooling/">maximum number of connections to hosts</a> (remote and local)</dd>

        <dt><strong>cassandra.pooling.local.max.requests</strong></dt>
        <dd>Optional.
          If specified defines the Cassandra <a href="http://docs.datastax.com/en/developer/java-driver/2.1/manual/pooling/">maximum number of concurrent requests per connection</a></dd>

        <dt><strong>cassandra.pooling.timeout</strong></dt>
        <dd>Optional.
          If specified defines the Cassandra <a href="http://docs.datastax.com/en/developer/java-driver/2.1/manual/pooling/">Specify timeout while not locationg pool</a>. Should be higher than sockets timeout.</dd>

        <dt><strong>cassandra.pooling.heartbeat.timeout</strong></dt>
        <dd>Optional.
          If specified defines the Cassandra <a href="http://docs.datastax.com/en/developer/java-driver/2.1/manual/pooling/">Specify heartbeat timeout</a></dd>

        <dt><strong>mailbox.max.retry.acl</strong></dt>
        <dd>Optional. Defaults to 1000.<br/> Controls the number of retries upon Cassandra ACL updates.</dd>
        <dt><strong>mailbox.max.retry.modseq</strong></dt>
        <dd>Optional. Defaults to 100000.<br/> Controls the number of retries upon Cassandra ModSeq generation.</dd>
        <dt><strong>mailbox.max.retry.uid</strong></dt>
        <dd>Optional. Defaults to 100000.<br/> Controls the number of retries upon Cassandra Uid generation.</dd>
        <dt><strong>mailbox.max.retry.message.flags.update</strong></dt>
        <dd>Optional. Defaults to 1000.<br/> Controls the number of retries upon Cassandra flags update, in MessageMapper.</dd>
        <dt><strong>mailbox.max.retry.message.id.flags.update</strong></dt>
        <dd>Optional. Defaults to 1000.<br/> Controls the number of retries upon Cassandra flags update, in MessageIdMapper.</dd>
        <dt><strong>fetch.advance.row.count</strong></dt>
        <dd>Optional. Defaults to 1000.<br/> Controls the number of remaining rows we should wait before prefetch when paging.</dd>
        <dt><strong>chunk.size.flags.update</strong></dt>
        <dd>Optional. Defaults to 20.<br/> Controls the number of messages flags updates to be performed concurently by MessageMapper.</dd>
        <dt><strong>chunk.size.message.read</strong></dt>
        <dd>Optional. Defaults to 100.<br/> Controls the number of messages to be retrieved in parallel.</dd>
        <dt><strong>chunk.size.expunge</strong></dt>
        <dd>Optional. Defaults to 100.<br/> Controls the number of messages to be expunged in parallel.</dd>
        <dt><strong>mailbox.blob.part.size</strong></dt>
        <dd>Optional. Defaults to 102400 (100KB).<br/> Controls the size of blob parts used to store messages.</dd>
        <dt><strong>migration.v1.v2.on.the.fly</strong></dt>
        <dd>Optional. Defaults to false.<br/> Controls wether v1 to v2 migration should be run on the fly.</dd>
        <dt><strong>migration.v1.v2.thread.count</strong></dt>
        <dd>Optional. Defaults to 2.<br/> Controls the number of threads used to asynchronously migrate from v1 to v2.</dd>
        <dt><strong>migration.v1.v2.queue.length</strong></dt>
        <dd>Optional. Defaults to 1000.<br/> Controls the queue size of v1 to v2 migration task. Drops when full.</dd>
        <dt><strong>migration.v1.read.fetch.size</strong></dt>
        <dd>Optional. Defaults to 10.<br/> Controls the fetch size of the request to retrieve all messages stored in V1 during the migration process.</dd>
      </dl>


<p>If you want more explanation about Cassandra configuration, you should visit the dedicated <a href="http://docs.datastax.com/en/cassandra/2.1/cassandra/gettingStartedCassandraIntro.html">documentation</a>.</p>

  </section>

  <section name="Cassandra migration process">
    <p>Cassandra upgrades implies the creation of a new table. Thus restarting James is needed, as new tables are created on restart.</p>

    <p>Once done, we ship code that tries to read from new tables, and if not possible backs up to old tables. You can thus safely run
    without running additional migrations.</p>

    <p>On the fly migration can be enabled. However, one might want to force the migration in a controlled fashion, and update
    automatically current schema version used (assess in the database old versions is no more used, as the corresponding tables are empty).
    Note that this process is safe: we ensure the service is not running concurrently on this James instance, that it does not bump
    version upon partial failures, that race condition in version upgrades will be idempotent, etc...</p>

    <p>These schema updates can be triggered by <a href="manage-webadmin.html">webadmin</a> using the Cassandra backend.</p>

    <p>Note that currently the progress can be tracked by logs.</p>
  </section>

</body>

</document>
