<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
  or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
  distributed with this work for additional information
  regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
  to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
  "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
  with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
  software distributed under the License is distributed on an
  "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
  KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
  specific language governing permissions and limitations
  under the License.    
-->
<document>

<properties>
 <title>Apache James Server 3 - DNS Service Configuration</title>
</properties>

<body>
 
 <section name="DNS Service Configuration">

    <subsection name="dnsservice.xml">

      <p>Consult <a href="https://github.com/apache/james-project/tree/master/server/app/src/main/resources/dnsservice.xml">dnsservice.xml</a> in GIT to get some examples and hints.</p>

      <p>Specifies DNS Server information for use by various components inside Apache James Server.</p>

      <p>DNS Transport services are controlled by a configuration block in
         the dnsservice.xml. This block affects SMTP remote delivery.</p>
    
      <p>The dnsservice tag defines the boundaries of the configuration
         block. It encloses all the relevant configuration for the DNS server.
         The behavior of the DNS service is controlled by the attributes and
         children of this tag.</p> 
    
      <dl>
        <dt><strong>servers</strong></dt>
        <dd>Information includes a list of DNS Servers to be used by James.  These are 
           specified by the server elements, each of which is a child element of the 
           servers element.  Each server element is the IP address of a single DNS server. 
           The servers element can have multiple server children. Enter ip address of your DNS server, one IP address per server 
         element. If no DNS servers are found and you have not specified any below, 127.0.0.1 will be used </dd>
        <dt><strong>autodiscover</strong></dt>
        <dd>true or false -  If you use autodiscover and add DNS servers manually a combination of all the DNS servers will be used
            If autodiscover is true, James will attempt to autodiscover the DNS servers configured on your underlying system.
            Currently, this works if the OS has a unix-like /etc/resolv.xml,
            or the system is Windows based with ipconfig or winipcfg. Change autodiscover to false if you would like to turn off autodiscovery 
            and set the DNS servers manually in the servers section </dd>
        <dt><strong>authoritative</strong></dt>
        <dd><strong>true/false</strong> - This tag specifies whether or not 
           to require authoritative (non-cached) DNS records; to only accept DNS responses that are 
           authoritative for the domain. It is primarily useful in an intranet/extranet environment.
           This should always be <strong>false</strong> unless you understand the implications.</dd>
        <dt><strong>maxcachesize</strong></dt>
        <dd>Maximum number of entries to maintain in the DNS cache (typically 50000)</dd>
        <dt><strong>singleIPperMX</strong></dt>
        <dd>true or false (default) - Specifies if Apache James Server must try a single server for each multihomed mx host</dd>
      </dl>
      
    </subsection>
    
  </section>
</body>

</document>

