<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
  or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
  distributed with this work for additional information
  regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
  to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
  "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
  with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
  software distributed under the License is distributed on an
  "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
  KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
  specific language governing permissions and limitations
  under the License.    
-->
<document>

    <properties>
        <title>Apache James Server 3 - Server Wide Configuration</title>
    </properties>

    <body>

        <section name="Server Wide Configuration">

            <subsection name="Introduction">

                <p>There are a number of global configuration files that do not fall into any one
                    component. They have effects that are global in scope across the server.</p>

                <p>Some of these files are crucial, while others can be ignored by any but the most sophisticated
                    server administrators.</p>

            </subsection>

            <subsection name="spring-server.xml">

                <p>In James distribution, the spring files are located under conf/context folder and splitted into a main
                    file (james-server-context.xml) which imports 3 other files (1 per mailbox type): james-mailbox-jpa-context.xml,
                    james-mailbox-memory-context.xml.</p>

                <p>Consult <a href="https://github.com/apache/james-project/tree/master/server/container/spring/src/main/resources/META-INF/org/apache/james/spring-server.xml">spring-server.xml</a> in GIT to
                    get some examples and hints.</p>

                <p>spring beans files are the place where the Apache James Server wiring is done. It should be modified only by expert-users.</p>

                <p>In combination with james-database.properties and META-INF/persistence.xml, the datasource to access the database is defined in spring-server.xml</p>

            </subsection>

            <subsection name="james-database.properties">

                <p>This configuration file is only relevant when using JPA, with Spring or Guice.</p>

                <p>Consult <a href="https://github.com/apache/james-project/tree/master/server/apps/spring-app/src/main/resources/james-database.properties">james-database.properties</a> in GIT to get some examples and hints.</p>

                <p>The database connection in database.properties</p>

                <p>James has the capacity to use a JDBC-compatible database for storage of both message and user
                    data. This section explains how to configure James to utilize a database for storage.</p>

                <p>To avoid vendor-specific issues, the JPA (Java Persistence Architecture) is used (using the Apache OpenJPA implementation).</p>

                <p>There must be a database instance accessible from the James server.  An account with appropriate
                    privileges (select, insert, delete into tables, and on initial startup creation of tables) and
                    with sufficient quota for the data to be inserted into the database must be available.</p>

                <p>Also, since James will use JDBC to access the database, an appropriate JDBC driver must be
                    available for installation. You can place the JDBC driver jar in the conf/lib folder, it will
                    be automatically loaded.</p>
                <p>Database configuration</p>
                <dl>
                    <dt><strong>database.driverClassName</strong></dt>
                    <dd>The class name of the database driver to be used.</dd>
                    <dt><strong>database.url</strong></dt>
                    <dd>The JDBC connection URL for your database/driver.</dd>
                    <dt><strong>database.username</strong></dt>
                    <dd>The user id of the database account to be used by this connection.</dd>
                    <dt><strong>database.password</strong></dt>
                    <dd>The password of the database account to be used by this connection.</dd>
                    <dt><strong>vendorAdapter.database</strong></dt>
                    <dd>Supported adapters are: DB2, DERBY, H2, HSQL, INFORMIX, MYSQL, ORACLE, POSTGRESQL, SQL_SERVER, SYBASE .</dd>
                    <dt><strong>openjpa.streaming</strong></dt>
                    <dd>true or false - Use streaming for Blobs. This is only supported on a limited set of databases atm. You
                        should check if its supported by your DB before enable it. See <a href="http://openjpa.apache.org/builds/latest/docs/manual/ref_guide_mapping_jpa.html">http://openjpa.apache.org/builds/latest/docs/manual/ref_guide_mapping_jpa.html</a> (#7.11. LOB Streaming).</dd>
                </dl>

                <p>NOTE: all<code>openjpa.*</code> properties will be passed to OpenJPA library as configuration See <a href="https://openjpa.apache.org/builds/3.2.2/apache-openjpa/docs/ref_guide_conf_openjpa.html">https://openjpa.apache.org/builds/3.2.2/apache-openjpa/docs/ref_guide_conf_openjpa.html</a> for a complete list </p>

                <p>The JPA datasource and connection pooling can be delegated to commons-dbcp2 - the library dependency has to be present in classpath for it to be enabled. dbcp2 properties can be configured through james-database.properties - all properties prefixed with <code>datasource.*</code> will be passed to DBCP2 library via <code>openjpa.ConnectionProperties</code> OpenJPA property. The corresponding definitions and default values can be found in the <a href="https://commons.apache.org/proper/commons-dbcp/configuration.html">dbcp documentation</a>, some of the properties (but not limited to)</p>
                <ul>
                    <li>datasource.testOnBorrow</li>
                    <li>datasource.validationQueryTimeoutSec</li>
                    <li>datasource.validationQuery</li>
                    <li>datasource.initialSize</li>
                    <li>datasource.minIdle</li>
                    <li>datasource.maxTotal</li>
                </ul>
                <p>NOTE: Connection poolling requires that <code>openjpa.Multithreaded</code> property is set to <code>true</code> (default)</p>
                <p>Note for postgresql databases: Add <code>standard_conforming_strings=off</code> to your postgresql.xml, otherwise you
                    will get <code>""Invalid escape string Hint: Escape string must be empty or one character. {prepstmnt 174928937
                    SELECT t0.mailbox_id, t0.mailbox_highest_modseq, t0.mailbox_last_uid, t0.mailbox_name, t0.mailbox_namespace,
                    t0.mailbox_uid_validity, t0.user_name FROM public.james_mailbox t0 WHERE (t0.mailbox_name LIKE ?
                        ESCAPE '\\' AND t0.user_name = ? AND t0.mailbox_namespace = ?) [params=?, ?, ?]} [code=0, state=22025]"</code></p>

            </subsection>

            <subsection name="META-INF/persistence.xml">

                <p>Consult <a href="https://github.com/apache/james-project/tree/master/server/apps/spring-app/src/main/resources/META-INF/persistence.xml">META-INF/persistence.xml</a> in GIT to get some examples and hints.</p>

                <p>The JPA mapping and properties are defined in the in META-INF/persistence.xml.</p>

                <p>You can override the definition in external file and importing the external file in the persistence.xml (see jpa-mappings.xml provided example in GIT)</p>

                <source>
                    &lt;mapping-file&gt;META-INF/jpa-mappings.xml&lt;/mapping-file&gt;</source>

            </subsection>

            <subsection name="jmx.properties">

                <p>Consult <a href="https://github.com/apache/james-project/tree/master/server/apps/spring-app/src/main/resources/jmx.properties">jmx.properties</a> in GIT to get some examples and hints.</p>

                <p>This is used to configure the JMX MBean server via which all management is achieved (also used by via the james-cli).</p>

                <dl>
                    <dt><strong>jmx.enabled</strong></dt>
                    <dd>(Guice only). Boolean. Should the JMX server be enabled? Defaults to `true`.</dd>
                    <dt><strong>jmx.address</strong></dt>
                    <dd>The IP address (host name) the MBean Server will bind/listen to.</dd>
                    <dt><strong>jmx.port</strong></dt>
                    <dd>The port number the MBean Server will bind/listen to.</dd>
                </dl>

                <p>To access from a remote location, it has been reported that <code>-Dcom.sun.management.jmxremote.ssl=false</code> is
                    needed in the startup script.</p>

                <b>JMX Security</b>

                <p>Guice only</p>

                <p>In order to set up JMX authentication, we need to put <code>jmxremote.password</code> and <code>jmxremote.access</code> file
                    to <code>/conf</code> directory.</p>

                <p><code>jmxremote.password</code>: define the username and password, that will be used by the client (here is james-cli)</p>

                <p>File's content example:</p>
                <pre><code>
                james-admin pass1
                </code></pre>

                <p><code>jmxremote.access</code>: define the pair of username and access permission</p>

                <p>File's content example:</p>
                <pre><code>
                james-admin readwrite
                </code></pre>

                <p>When James runs with option <code>-Djames.jmx.credential.generation=true</code>, James will automatically
                    generate <code>jmxremote.password</code> if the file does not exist.
                    Then the default username is <code>james-admin</code> and a random password. This option defaults to true.</p>


            </subsection>

            <subsection name="sqlResources.xml">

                <p>Consult <a href="https://github.com/apache/james-project/tree/master/server/apps/spring-app/src/main/resources/sqlResources.xml">sqlResources.xml</a> in GIT to get some examples and hints.</p>

                <p>This file is deprecated but some mailets... still need it. The standard way to access database
                    is JPA, but some functionalities are not yet migrated and still need the sqlResources.xml resources.</p>

                <p>The precise SQL statements used by Apache James Server to modify and view data stored in the database
                    are specified in sqlResources.xml file.</p>

                <p>If you are using a SQL database with unusual SQL commands or data types, you may
                    need to add special entries to this file.  The James team
                    does try to keep sqlResources.xml updated, so if you do run into a
                    special case, please let us know.</p>

                <p>Also, if the database tables are not created a priori, but rather are to be created by James
                    upon startup, special attention should be paid to the "create table" statements in this file.  Such
                    statements tend to be both very database and very database instance specific.</p>

            </subsection>

            <subsection name="jvm.properties">

                <p>This configuration file is only relevant when using Guice.</p>

                <p>It may contain any additional system properties for tweaking JVM execution.
                    When you normally would add a command line option <code>-Dmy.property=whatever</code>,
                    you can put it in this file as <code>my.property=whatever</code> instead.
                    These properties will be added as system properties on server start.</p>

                <p>Note that in some rare cases this might not work,
                    when a property affects very early JVM start behaviour.</p>

                <p>For testing purposes, you may specify a different file path via the
                    command line option <code>-Dextra.props=/some/other/jvm.properties</code>.</p>

            <p>Some tuning can be done via system properties. This includes:</p>

            <dl>
                <dt><strong>james.message.memory.threshold</strong></dt>
                <dd>(Optional). String (size, integer + size units, example: `12 KIB`, supported units are bytes KIB MIB GIB TIB). Defaults to 100KIB. <br/>
                    This governs the threshold MimeMessageInputStreamSource relies on for storing MimeMessage content on disk. <br/>
                    Below, data is stored in memory. Above data is stored on disk.
                    Lower values will lead to longer processing time but will minimize heap memory usage. Modern SSD hardware
                    should however support a high throughput. Higher values will lead to faster single mail processing at the cost
                    of higher heap usage.
                </dd>

                <dt><strong>james.message.usememorycopy</strong></dt>
                <dd>Optional. Boolean. Defaults to false. Recommended value is false. <br/>
                    Should MimeMessageWrapper use a copy of the message in memory? Or should bigger message exceeding james.message.memory.threshold be copied to temporary files?</dd>

                <dt><strong>james.lifecycle.leak.detection.mode</strong></dt>
                <dd>Optional. Allowed values are: none, simple, advanced, testing. Defaults to simple. <br/>
                    Mode level of resource leak detection. It is used to detect a resource not be disposed of before it's garbage-collected. Example `MimeMessageInputStreamSource` <br/>
                        - none: Disables resource leak detection.<br/>
                        - simple: Enables output a simplistic error log if a leak is encountered and would free the resources (default). <br/>
                        - advanced: Enables output an advanced error log implying the place of allocation of the underlying object and would free resources. <br/>
                        - testing: Enables output an advanced error log implying the place of allocation of the underlying object and rethrow an error, that action is being taken by the development team. <br/>
                </dd>

                <dt><strong>james.protocols.mdc.hostname</strong></dt>
                <dd>Optional. Boolean. Defaults to true. <br/>
                    Should we add the host in the MDC logging context for incoming IMAP, SMTP, POP3? Doing so, a DNS resolution
                    is attempted for each incoming connection, which can be costly. Remote IP is always added to the logging context.</dd>

                <dt><strong>james.blob.id.hash.encoding</strong></dt>
                <dd>Optional. String. Defaults to base64Url. <br/>
                    The encoding type when encode blobId. The support value are: base16, hex, base32, base32Hex, base64, base64Url.</dd>
            </dl>

            </subsection>

        </section>

    </body>

</document>

