<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
  or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
  distributed with this work for additional information
  regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
  to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
  "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
  with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
  software distributed under the License is distributed on an
  "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
  KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
  specific language governing permissions and limitations
  under the License.    
-->
<document>

 <properties>
  <title>Apache James Server 3 - Mailet Container Configuration</title>
 </properties>

<body>

  <section name="Mailet Container Configuration">

      <p>This documents explains how to configure Mail processing. Mails pass through the MailetContainer. The
          MailetContainer is a Matchers (condition for executing a mailet) and Mailets (execution units that perform
          actions based on incoming mail) pipeline arranged into processors (List of mailet/matcher pairs allowing
          better logical organisation). You can read more about these concepts on <a href="feature-mailetcontainer.html">the mailet container feature description</a>.</p>

      <p>Apache James Server includes a number of pre-packaged <a href="dev-provided-mailets.html">Mailets and Matchers</a>.
      Futhermore, you can write and use with James your own <a href="dev-extend-matcher.html">custom matchers</a> and
      <a href="dev-extend-mailet.html">custom mailets</a>.</p>

      <p>Consult <a href="https://github.com/apache/james-project/tree/master/server/app/src/main/resources/mailetcontainer.xml">mailetcontainer.xml</a> in GIT to get some examples and hints.</p>

      <dl>
        <dt><strong>context.postmaster</strong></dt>
        <dd>The body of this element is the address that the server 
            will consider its postmaster address.  This address will be listed as the sender address 
            of all error messages that originate from James.  Also, all messages addressed to 
            postmaster@&lt;servername&gt;, where &lt;servername&gt; is one of the domain names whose 
            mail is being handled by James, will be redirected to this email address.
            Set this to the appropriate email address for error reports 
            If this is set to a non-local email address, the mail server
            will still function, but will generate a warning on startup.</dd>
          <dt><strong>spooler.threads</strong></dt>
          <dd>Number of simultaneous threads used to spool the mails. Set to zero, it disables mail processing - use with
              caution.</dd>
          <dt><strong>spooler.errorRepository</strong></dt>
          <dd>Mail repository to store email in after several unrecoverable errors. Mails failing processing, for which
              the Mailet Container could not handle Error, will be stored there after their processing had been attempted
              5 times. Note that if standard java Exception occurs, <b>Error handling</b> section below will be applied
              instead.</dd>
      </dl>

    <subsection name="The Mailet Tag">
    
      <p>Consider the following simple <strong>mailet</strong> tag:</p>
      &lt;mailet match="RemoteAddrNotInNetwork=127.0.0.1" class="ToProcessor"&gt;<br/>
      &lt;processor&gt;spam&lt;/processor&gt;<br/>
      &lt;/mailet&gt;<br/>
      
      <p>The mailet tag has two required attributes, <strong>match</strong> and <strong>class</strong>.</p>
      
      <p>The <strong>match</strong> attribute is set to the value of the specific Matcher class to be instantiated with a an 
      optional argument.  If present, the argument is separated from the Matcher class name by an '='.  Semantic 
      interpretation of the argument is left to the particular mailet.</p>
      
      <p>The <strong>class</strong> attribute is set to the value of the Mailet class that is to be instantiated.</p>
      
      <p>Finally, the children of the <strong>mailet</strong> tag define the configuration that is passed to the Mailet.  The 
      tags used in this section should have no attributes or children.  The names and bodies of the elements will be passed to 
      the mailet as (name, value) pairs.</p>
      
      <p>So in the example above, a Matcher instance of RemoteAddrNotInNetwork would be instantiated, and the value "127.0.0.1" 
      would be passed to the matcher.  The Mailet of the pair will be an instance of ToProcessor, and it will be passed the (name, value) 
      pair of ("processor", "spam").</p>
    
    </subsection>

    <subsection name="Error handling">
      <p>If an exception is encountered during the execution of a mailet or a matcher, the default behaviour is to
      process the mail using the <strong>error</strong> processor.</p>

      <p>The <strong>onMailetException</strong> property allows you to override this behaviour. You can specify another
          processor than the <strong>error</strong> one for handling the errors of this mailet. The <strong>ignore</strong> special value also
      allows to continue processing and ignore the error.</p>

      <p>Moreover, the <strong>onMatcherException</strong> allows you to override matcher error handling. You can
          specify another processor than the <strong>error</strong> one for handling the errors of this mailet. The <strong>matchall</strong>
          special value also allows you to match all recipients when there is an error. The <strong>nomatch</strong>
          special value also allows you to match no recipients when there is an error.</p>

      <p>Here is a short example to illustrate this:</p>

      <pre><code>&lt;mailet match=RecipientIsLocal class="LocalDelivery"&gt;
    &lt;onMailetException&gt;deliveryError&lt;/onMailetException&gt;
    &lt;onMatcherException&gt;nomatch&lt;/onMatcherException&gt;
&lt;/mailet&gt;
      </code></pre>
    </subsection>
  
  </section>

</body>
</document>
