<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
  or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
  distributed with this work for additional information
  regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
  to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
  "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
  with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
  software distributed under the License is distributed on an
  "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
  KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
  specific language governing permissions and limitations
  under the License.
-->
<document>

    <properties>
        <title>Apache James Server 3 - JMAP Configuration</title>
    </properties>

    <body>

        <section name="JMAP configuration">

            <p><a href="https://jmap.io/">JMAP</a>  is intended to be a new standard for email clients to connect to mail
                stores. It therefore intends to primarily replace IMAP + SMTP submission. It is also designed to be more
                generic. It does not replace MTA-to-MTA SMTP transmission.</p>

            <p>Cassandra Guice proposes a JMAP implementation.</p>

            <subsection name="jmap.properties">

                <p>Consult <a href="https://github.com/apache/james-project/blob/master/server/apps/distributed-app/sample-configuration/jmap.properties">jmap.properties</a> in GIT to get some examples and hints.</p>

                <br/>

                <dl>
                    <dt><strong>enabled</strong></dt>
                    <dd>true/false. Governs whether JMAP should be enabled</dd>

                    <dt><strong>jmap.port</strong></dt>
                    <dd>Optional. Defaults to 80. The port this server will be listening on. This value must be a valid
                    port, ranging between 1 and 65535 (inclusive)</dd>

                    <dt><strong>tls.keystoreURL</strong></dt>
                    <dd>Keystore to be used for generating authentication tokens for password authentication mechanism.
                    This should not be the same keystore than the ones used by TLS based protocols.</dd>

                    <dt><strong>tls.secret</strong></dt>
                    <dd>Password used to read the keystore</dd>

                    <dt><strong>jwt.publickeypem.url</strong></dt>
                    <dd>Optional. Coma separated list of RSA public keys URLs to validate JWT tokens allowing requests to bypass authentication.
                        Defaults to an empty list.</dd>

                    <dt><strong>url.prefix</strong></dt>
                    <dd>Optional. Configuration urlPrefix for JMAP routes.</dd>
                    <dd>Default value: http://localhost.</dd>

                    <dt><strong>websocket.url.prefix</strong></dt>
                    <dd>Optional. URL for JMAP WebSocket route</dd>
                    <dd>Default value: ws://localhost</dd>

                    <dt><strong>upload.max.size</strong></dt>
                    <dd>Optional. Configuration max size Upload in new JMAP-RFC-8621.</dd>
                    <dd>Default value: 30M. Supported units are B (bytes) K (KB) M (MB) G (GB).</dd>

                    <dt><strong>email.send.max.size</strong></dt>
                    <dd>Optional. Configuration max size for message created in both JMAP Draft amd RFC-8621.</dd>
                    <dd>Default value: None. Supported units are B (bytes) K (KB) M (MB) G (GB).</dd>

                    <dt><strong>max.size.attachments.per.mail</strong></dt>
                    <dd>Optional. Defaults to 20MB. RFC-8621 <code>maxSizeAttachmentsPerEmail</code> advertised to JMAP
                        client as part of the <code>urn:ietf:params:jmap:mail</code> capability. This needs to be at
                        least 33% lower than <code>email.send.max.size</code> property (in order to account for text body,
                        headers, base64 encoding and MIME structures). JMAP clients would use this property in order not
                        to create too big emails.</dd>
                    <dd>Default value: None. Supported units are B (bytes) K (KB) M (MB) G (GB).</dd>

                    <dt><strong>view.email.query.enabled</strong></dt>
                    <dd>Optional boolean. Defaults to false.</dd>
                    <dd>Should simple Email/query be resolved against a Cassandra projection, or should we resolve them against OpenSearch?
                        This enables a higher resilience, but the projection needs to be correctly populated.</dd>

                    <dt><strong>user.provisioning.enabled</strong></dt>
                    <dd>Optional boolean. Defaults to true.</dd>
                    <dd>Governs whether authenticated users that do not exist locally should be created in the users repository.
                    </dd>

                    <dt><strong>authentication.strategy.draft</strong></dt>
                    <dd>List[String] with delimiter ",". Defaults to AccessTokenAuthenticationStrategy,JWTAuthenticationStrategy,
                        QueryParameterAccessTokenAuthenticationStrategy.</dd>
                    <dd>Specify which authentication strategies system admin want to use for JMAP draft server.
                        The implicit package name is "org.apache.james.jmap.http". If you have a custom authentication strategy outside this package, you have to specify its FQDN.
                        If no authentication strategy is specified, JMAP draft server will fallback to default strategies:
                    AccessTokenAuthenticationStrategy, JWTAuthenticationStrategy, QueryParameterAccessTokenAuthenticationStrategy.</dd>

                    <dt><strong>authentication.strategy.rfc8621</strong></dt>
                    <dd>List[String] with delimiter ",". Defaults to JWTAuthenticationStrategy,BasicAuthenticationStrategy.</dd>
                    <dd>Specify which authentication strategies system admin want to use for JMAP RFC-8621 server.
                        The implicit package name is "org.apache.james.jmap.http". If you have a custom authentication strategy outside this package, you have to specify its FQDN.
                        If no authentication strategy is specified, JMAP RFC-8621 server will fallback to default strategies:
                    JWTAuthenticationStrategy, BasicAuthenticationStrategy.</dd>

                    <dt><strong>jmap.version.default</strong></dt>
                    <dd>Optional string. Defaults to draft. Allowed values: draft, rfc-8621.</dd>
                    <dd>Which version of the JMAP protocol should be served when none supplied in the Accept header.
                    Defaults to draft for legacy reasons (avoid breaking changes) but setting the value to
                    rfc-8621 allow compatibility with other third party apps.</dd>

                    <dt><strong>dynamic.jmap.prefix.resolution.enabled</strong></dt>
                    <dd>Optional boolean. Defaults to false. Supported Jmap session endpoint returns dynamic prefix in response.
                        When its config is true, and the HTTP request to Jmap session endpoint has a `X-JMAP-PREFIX` header with the value `http://new-domain/prefix`,
                        then `apiUrl, downloadUrl, uploadUrl, eventSourceUrl, webSocketUrl` in response will be changed with a new prefix. Example: The `apiUrl` will be "http://new-domain/prefix/jmap".
                        If the HTTP request to Jmap session endpoint has the `X-JMAP-WEBSOCKET-PREFIX` header with the value `ws://new-domain/prefix`,
                        then `capabilities."urn:ietf:params:jmap:websocket".url` in response will be "ws://new-domain/prefix/jmap/ws".
                    </dd>

                    <dt><strong>webpush.prevent.server.side.request.forgery</strong></dt>
                    <dd>Optional boolean. Prevent server side request forgery by preventing calls to the private network
                        ranges. Defaults to true, can be disabled for testing.
                    </dd>

                    <dt><strong>cassandra.filter.projection.activated</strong></dt>
                    <dd>Optional boolean. Defaults to false. Casandra backends only. Whether to use or not the Cassandra projection
                        for JMAP filters. This projection optimizes reads, but needs to be correctly populated. Turning it on on
                        systems with filters already defined would result in those filters to be not read.
                    </dd>
                </dl>

            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Wire tapping">
                <p>Enabling <b>TRACE</b> on <b>org.apache.james.jmap.wire</b> enables reactor-netty wiretap, logging of
                all incoming and outgoing requests, outgoing requests. This will log also potentially sensible information
                like authentication credentials.</p>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="OIDC set up">
                <p>The use of <code>XUserAuthenticationStrategy</code> allow delegating the authentication responsibility to a third party system,
                    which could be used to set up authentication against an OIDC provider.</p>
                <p>We do supply an <a href="https://github.com">example</a> of such a setup. It combines the
                    <a href="https://www.keycloak.org/">Keycloack</a> OIDC provider with the
                    <a href="https://www.krakend.io/">Krackend</a> API gateway, but usage of similar technologies is definitely doable.</p>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="JMAP-draft vs JMAP-RFC-8621">
                <p>James had been supporting an implementation based on an early specification of JMAP, what we call here
                <em>JMAP-draft</em> version. But the protocol went under a lot of changes until its finalization as an
                official RFC.</p>

                <p>The finalized version of JMAP regarding the core specifications [<a href="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc8620">RFC-8620</a>]
                and the mail specifications [<a href="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc8621">RFC-8621</a>] are being
                currently implemented in James (<em>JMAP-RFC-8621</em> version). It's supposed to replace at term the
                <em>JMAP-draft</em> version.</p>

                <p>Meanwhile, both versions will be available. The version by default will be <em>JMAP-draft</em> during
                the time it takes to implement the new version. If you want to use a specific version for a request,
                you will need to add an extra <em>jmapVersion</em> field in your <b>Accept</b> header of your JMAP request:</p>

                <ul>
                    <li><b>JMAP-draft</b>: <em>Accept: application/json; jmapVersion=draft</em></li>
                    <li><b>JMAP-RFC-8621</b>: <em>Accept: application/json; jmapVersion=rfc-8621</em></li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Annotated specification">
                <p>The <a href="https://github.com/apache/james-project/tree/master/server/protocols/jmap-rfc-8621/doc/specs/spec">annotated documentation</a>
                presents the limits of the JMAP RFC-8621 implementation part of the Apache James project. We furthermore implement
                    <a href="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc8887">JSON Meta Application Protocol (JMAP) Subprotocol for WebSocket</a>.</p>

                <p>Some methods / types are not yet implemented, some implementations are naive, and the PUSH is not supported yet.</p>

                <p>Users are invited to read these limitations before using actively the JMAP RFC-8621 implementation, and should ensure their
                client applications only uses supported operations.</p>

                <p>Contributions enhancing support are furthermore welcomed.</p>

                <ul>The list of tested JMAP clients are:
                    <li><a href="https://open-paas.org/">OpenPaaS</a> is actively using the draft version of the JMAP implementation. Migration to
                    RFC-8621 is planned.</li>
                    <li>Experiments had been run on top of <a href="https://github.com/iNPUTmice/lttrs-android">LTT.RS</a>. Version in the Accept
                        headers needs to be explicitly set to `rfc-8621`. <a href="https://github.com/linagora/james-project/pull/4089">Read more</a>.</li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="JMAP auto-configuration">

                <p><a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/rfc8620">RFC-8620</a> defining JMAP core RFC defines precisely service location.</p>

                <p>James already redirects `http://jmap.domain.tld/.well-known/jmap` to the JMAP session.</p>

                <p>You can further help your clients by publishing extra SRV records.</p>

                <pre><code>_jmap._tcp.domain.tld. 3600        IN    SRV    0 1 443 jmap.domain.tld.</code></pre>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Reverse-proxy set up">
                <p>James implementation adds the value of <code>X-Real-IP</code> header as part of the logging MDC.</p>

                <p>This allows for reverse proxies to cary other the IP address of the client down to the JMAP server for diagnostic purpose.</p>
            </subsection>
        </section>

    </body>

</document>
