<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
  or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
  distributed with this work for additional information
  regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
  to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
  "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
  with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
  software distributed under the License is distributed on an
  "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
  KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
  specific language governing permissions and limitations
  under the License.    
-->
<document>

    <properties>
        <title>Apache James Server 3 - Quota Configuration</title>
    </properties>

    <body>

        <section name="Events System Configuration">

            This configuration applies only to Spring wiring.

            <p>Consult <a href="https://github.com/apache/james-project/tree/master/server/app/src/main/resources/events.xml">events.xml</a> in GIT to get some examples and hints.</p>

            <p>Use this configuration to define the type of Event System you want.</p>

            <p>
                James relies on an event system. Each operations performed on the mailbox will trigger related events. Some software
                components (MailboxListeners) can register themselves on this event system to be called when an event is fired.
            </p>

            <p>
                Here are typical use cases for Mailbox Listeners (non exhaustive list) :
                <ul>
                    <li>Message search indexation, for instance in Lucene or ElasticSearch</li>
                    <li>Local cache invalidation (caching mailbox project)</li>
                    <li>Quota calculation</li>
                    <li>IMAP IDLE feature : live notification of actions performed on a mailbox, allowing publish subscribe on mailboxes events</li>
                    <li>Message Sequence Number consistence</li>
                </ul>
                The Mailbox Listeners can be classified in two categories :
                <ul>
                    <li>Mailbox registered : The mailbox listener is only notified on events affecting this mailbox. IDLE is a good example of this.</li>
                    <li>Global Listeners : This event listener is triggered upon each events.</li>
                </ul>
                Note that Global Listeners can also be classified in two categories :
                <ul>
                    <li>Those which needs to be triggered only once in your cluster. For instance ElasticSearch indexing is an example of this.</li>
                    <li>Those which needs to be triggered on each servers. For instance, each Lucene indexer needs to be triggered on each server
                        for the search feature to stay consistent.</li>
                </ul>
            </p>

            <p>
                The default implementation is a synchronous in memory event system. The performance are really good, as their is no need to serialize
                events, and no network overhead. However, this event system is limited to one computer and you might want a distributed systems.
            </p>

            <p>
                Other implementations, distributed environment friendly are available.
            </p>

            <p>
                The simplest one is broadcast based. Each James servers listen the same message queue, and each James server will be notified upon events.
                Here are the pros and cons of this implementations :
                <ul>
                    Pros:
                    <li>It supports every type of listener described above</li>
                    <li>It allows you to scale your James infrastructure without changing your middlewares. You just need a message queue</li>
                    Cons :
                    <li>Your scalability is limited as each servers is notified on all events</li>
                    <li>Network overhead on event transmissions</li>
                    <li>Event serialization and deserialization</li>
                </ul>
                To use this implementation, you need two other components (that will be discussed) : a publishing system and an event serializer
            </p>

            <p>
                The other mode is based on registrations.
                Each server reads messages from a dedicated message queue, and other servers send messages addressed to this sever on this message queue.
                Registrations are performed on an eternal data-store supporting document deletion after a fixed amount of time.
                These registrations are periodically refreshed. This data-store is then triggered on event generation, that, if needed are serialized and
                send to the given queues.
                The pros and cons of this implementations are :
                <ul>
                    Pros :
                    <li>Linear scalability</li>
                    <li>A server receives only events concerning him</li>
                    Cons :
                    <li>Possible event serialization costs</li>
                    <li>Registration and registration refresh costs</li>
                    <li>Need to find interested servers on event delivery</li>
                    <li>Network overhead on event transmissions</li>
                </ul>
            </p>

            <h2>Failure modes</h2>

            <ul>
                Default implementation :
                <li>The default implementation might not deliver some events on server stop.</li>
            </ul>

            <ul>
                Broadcast implementation :
                <li>The broadcast implementation might not deliver some events on server stop.</li>
                <li>The broadcast implementation is tight to limitation of the underlying publisher.</li>
            </ul>

            <ul>
                Registered implementation :
                <li>The registered implementation might not deliver some events on server stop.</li>
                <li>The registered implementation is tight to limitation of the underlying publisher, and underlying registration system.</li>
            </ul>

            <h2>Publisher</h2>

            <p>
                Available implementation is Kafka based. Kafka ensure at least one delivery. This means some messages might be
                delivered two times. You need to compile and run James using Java 8 in order to use the Kafka messaging system.
            </p>

            <h2>Event serializer</h2>

            <p>There are two types of event serialization systems :
                <ul>
                    <li>Json : events are converted to JSON</li>
                    <li>Message Pack : a binary representation of JSON. 2 times smaller in average but two times longer to compute. It allows you to trade
                    bandwidth and data readability against CPU time.</li>
                </ul>
            </p>

            <h2>Registration systems</h2>

            <p>
                Available implementation is based on Cassandra. It is used on an AP fashion, enforcing availability instead of consistency. Some
                messages might get delivered to no more registered servers. This is just extra work. Worst, messages might not be delivered to
                recently registered servers. But we make sure that we have the more up to date version of the registrations we can, and will not time out in
                the face of network partitions, nor enforce some default behaviour.
            </p>

        </section>

    </body>

</document>

