<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
  or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
  distributed with this work for additional information
  regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
  to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
  "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
  with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
  software distributed under the License is distributed on an
  "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
  KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
  specific language governing permissions and limitations
  under the License.    
-->
<document>

 <properties>
  <title>Apache James Server 3 - RabbitMQ Configuration</title>
 </properties>

<body>

  <section name="RabbitMQ Server Configuration">
      <p>
          RabbitMQ is used in distributed James in order to have a distributed MailQueue and distributed Event dispatching system.

          This configuration helps you configure components using RabbitMQ in case you want to setup a distributed James.
          And it is only applicable with Guice products.
      </p>
      <p>
          Consult <a href="https://github.com/apache/james-project/blob/master/dockerfiles/run/guice/cassandra-rabbitmq/destination/conf/rabbitmq.properties">rabbitmq.properties</a>
          in GIT to get some examples and hints.
      </p>

      <p>
          RabbitMQ Configuration
      </p>
      <dl>
          <dt><strong>uri</strong></dt>
          <dd>
              the amqp URI pointing to RabbitMQ server. Details about amqp URI format is in <a href="https://www.rabbitmq.com/uri-spec.html">RabbitMQ URI Specification</a>
          </dd>

          <dt><strong>management.uri</strong></dt>
          <dd>
              the URI pointing to RabbitMQ Management Service. James need to retrieve some information about listing queues from this service in runtime.
              Details about URI format is in <a href="https://www.rabbitmq.com/management.html#usage-ui">RabbitMQ Management URI</a>
          </dd>

          <dt><strong>management.user</strong></dt>
          <dd>username used to access management service</dd>

          <dt><strong>management.password</strong></dt>
          <dd>password used to access management service</dd>
      </dl>
  </section>

  <section name="RabbitMQ MailQueue Configuration">
      <p>
          RabbitMQ MailQueue Configuration
      </p>
      <p>
          James mail queue is a component acting like a queue where it can enqueue and dequeue mails.
          Beside of the basic features, it also allows some extra operations like getting size, browsing all items in the mail queue...
          One of the mailqueue implementation is using RabbitMQ.
          As RabbitMQ doesn't offer enough features to implement efficiently all mailqueue operations,
          this implementation relies on Cassandra.
      </p>
      <dl>
          <dt><strong>mailqueue.view.sliceWindow</strong></dt>
          <dd>
              James divide the view into slices, each slice contains data for a given period, sliceWindow parameter controls this period.
              This dividing of periods allows faster browsing of the mail queue. Tips for choosing sliceWindow are explained in
              <a href="https://github.com/apache/james-project/blob/master/dockerfiles/run/guice/cassandra-rabbitmq/destination/conf/rabbitmq.properties">rabbitmq.properties</a>
          </dd>

          <dt><strong>mailqueue.view.bucketCount</strong></dt>
          <dd>
              Mails in a mail queue are distributed across the underlying storage service.
              BucketCount describes how to be distributing mails to fit with your James setup
              Tips for choosing bucketCount are explained in
              <a href="https://github.com/apache/james-project/blob/master/dockerfiles/run/guice/cassandra-rabbitmq/destination/conf/rabbitmq.properties">rabbitmq.properties</a>
          </dd>

          <dt><strong>mailqueue.view.updateBrowseStartPace</strong></dt>
          <dd>
              To browse, James needs a starting point and to continuously update that point in runtime.
              UpdateBrowseStartPace describes the probability to update the starting point.
              Tips for choosing updateBrowseStartPace are explained in
              <a href="https://github.com/apache/james-project/blob/master/dockerfiles/run/guice/cassandra-rabbitmq/destination/conf/rabbitmq.properties">rabbitmq.properties</a>
          </dd>

          <dt><strong>mailqueue.size.metricsEnabled</strong></dt>
          <dd>
              By default, the metrics are disabled for the mail queue size.
              As computing the size of the mail queue is currently implemented on top of browse operation and thus have a linear complexity,
              sometimes it can get too big, making it impossible for the ES reporter to handle it correctly without crashing.
              It can be useful then to disable it.
              Tips for choosing metricsEnabled are explained in
              <a href="https://github.com/apache/james-project/blob/master/dockerfiles/run/guice/cassandra-rabbitmq/destination/conf/rabbitmq.properties">rabbitmq.properties</a>
          </dd>
      </dl>
  </section>

</body>

</document>
