<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
  or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
  distributed with this work for additional information
  regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
  to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
  "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
  with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
  software distributed under the License is distributed on an
  "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
  KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
  specific language governing permissions and limitations
  under the License.    
-->
<document>

 <properties>
  <title>Apache James Server 3 - Fetchmail Configuration</title>
 </properties>

<body>

  <section name="Fetchmail Configuration">

    This configuration file requires Spring wiring.

    <p>Consult <a href="https://github.com/apache/james-project/tree/master/server/app/src/main/resources/fetchmail.xml">fetchmail.xml</a> in GIT to get some examples and hints.</p>

    <p>Fetchmail acts as a gateway between an external message store such as an IMAP
    or POP3 server and James. Mail is fetched from the external message store and
    injected into the James input spool.</p>
    
    <p>Fetchmail  is useful when delivery via standard SMTP is not an option, as a
    means of consolidating mail delivered to several external accounts into a single
    James account, or to apply the mail processing capabilities of James to mail 
    stored in an external message store.</p>
    
    <p>Fetchmail has several configuration options that control the fetching and 
    filtering of mail injected into the James input spool. Once there, James' 
    flexible mail processing engine can be used to further process the mail, just as
    if it had been delivered via standard SMTP.</p>
    
    <p>
    <a href="#How_Fetchmail_Works">How Fetchmail Works</a><br/>
    <a href="#Fetchmail_Configuration_Parameters">Fetchmail Configuration Parameters</a><br/>
    <a href="#Fetchmail_Examples">Fetchmail Examples</a><br/>
    <a href="#Fetchmail_Caveats">Fetchmail Caveats</a><br/>
    <a href="#Fetchmail_Gmail">Fetchmail Gmail</a>
    </p>
    
  </section>
  
  <section name="How Fetchmail Works">
  
    <p>Mail is delivered by periodically running fetch tasks that read messages from
    an external message store and injects them into the James input spool. Fetch 
    tasks run concurrently.</p>
    
    <p>A set of filters applies to each fetch task. Each filter provides the ability
    to reject a message that matches the filter criteria. Rejected messages are not
    injected into the James input spool; they are either marked as seen or deleted.
    When a filter is configured to accept a message that matches its criteria, 
    messages are marked with a MailAttribute. This MailAttribute can be detected 
    within the James matcher/mailet chain, allowing further processing as 
    required.</p>
    
    <p>Each fetch task is associated with a single host server. Accounts are defined
    to the fetch task for each mailbox on the server from which mail is to be
    fetched. Accounts run consecutively.</p>
    
    <p>Optionally, the fetch task can be configured with an &lt;alllocal&gt; Account that
    generates an Account entry for each user defined in the James user repository.
    This removes the requirement to manually add or remove Account entries to the 
    Fetchmail configuration each time a James user is added or removed. Currently 
    this is only useful if the server supports virtual mailboxes that allow the same
    password to apply to all users within a domain.</p>
    
    <p>Accounts can be configured to deliver all mail for an Account to a specified
    recipient or to deduce the intended recipient from the mail headers.</p>
    
    <p>Accounts are normally configured to deliver all mail for an Account to a 
    specified recipient, ignoring the recipient in the mail headers. This works well
    in the majority of cases where a mailbox is guaranteed to contain mail for a sole
    mailbox recipient.</p>
    
    <p>Accounts are configured to deduce the intended recipient from the mail headers
    when a mailbox contains mail for several users, typically all users in a domain.
    Used alone, this is not foolproof as there are circumstances when a single unique
    recipient cannot be deduced from the mail headers alone. Used in conjunction with
    an appropriately configured &lt;alllocal&gt; account, it is always possible to deduce 
    the intended recipient when the recipient is a James user.</p>
  </section>
  
  <section name="Fetchmail Configuration Parameters">
  
    <p>The Fetchmail configuration parameters are part of the James configuration, 
    whose base file is <code>fetchmail.xml</code>. For clarity and flexibility, the 
    Fetchmail configuration parameters are stored in the file 
    <code>james-Fetchmail.xml</code>, which is referenced within 
    <code>fetchmail.xml</code>.</p>
    
    <p>The configuration parameters are described below.</p>
    
    <subsection name="Fetchmail">
    <p>The configuration block delimited by the <strong>Fetchmail</strong> tag 
    controls Fetchmail.</p>
    
    <p>The tag has these attributes:
    <dl>
    <dt><strong>enabled</strong></dt>
    <dd>A boolean. If &quot;true&quot;, the fetch tasks will be run periodically. If &quot;false&quot;, 
    no fetch tasks will be run. The default is &quot;false&quot;.</dd>
    </dl>
    </p>
    
    <p>The tag has these child tags (minimum cardinality, maximum cardinality):
    <ul>
    <li><strong><a href="#fetch">fetch</a></strong> (0, *)</li>
    </ul>
    </p>
    
    <p>
    <source>
    &lt;Fetchmail enabled=&quot;true&quot;&gt;
    ...
    &lt;/Fetchmail&gt;
    </source>
    </p>
    </subsection>
    
    <subsection name="fetch">
    <p>The <strong>fetch</strong> tag defines a fetch task to be run 
    periodically. Fetch tasks run concurrently.</p>
    
    <p>The tag has these attributes:
    <dl>
    <dt><strong>name</strong></dt>
    <dd>A string uniquely identifying the fetch task.</dd>
    </dl>
    </p>
    
    <p>The tag has these child tags (minimum cardinality, maximum cardinality):
    <ul>
      <li><strong><a href="#accounts">accounts</a></strong> (1, 1)</li>
      <li><strong><a href="#blacklist">blacklist</a></strong> (1, 1)</li>
      <li><strong><a href="#defaultdomain">defaultdomain</a></strong> (0, 1)</li>
      <li><strong><a href="#fetchall">fetchall</a></strong> (1, 1)</li>
      <li><strong><a href="#fetched">fetched</a></strong> (1, 1)</li>
      <li><strong><a href="#host">host</a></strong> (1, 1)</li>
      <li><strong><a href="#interval">interval</a></strong> (1, 1)</li>
      <li><strong><a href="#javaMailFolderName">javaMailFolderName</a></strong> (1, 1)</li>
      <li><strong><a href="#javaMailProperties">javaMailProperties</a></strong> (0, 1)</li>
      <li><strong><a href="#javaMailProviderName">javaMailProviderName</a></strong> (1, 1)</li>
      <li><strong><a href="#maxmessagesize">maxmessagesize</a></strong> (0, 1)</li>
      <li><strong><a href="#recipientnotfound">recipientnotfound</a></strong> (1, 1)</li>
      <li><strong><a href="#recursesubfolders">recursesubfolders</a></strong> (1, 1)</li>
      <li><strong><a href="#remoteReceivedHeader">remoteReceivedHeader</a></strong> (0, 1)</li>
      <li><strong><a href="#remoterecipient">remoterecipient</a></strong> (1, 1)</li>
      <li><strong><a href="#undeliverable">undeliverable</a></strong> (1, 1)</li>
      <li><strong><a href="#userundefined">userundefined</a></strong> (1, 1)</li>
    </ul>
    </p>
    
    <p>
    <source>
    &lt;fetch name=&quot;mydomain.com&quot;&gt;
    ...
    &lt;/fetch&gt;
    </source>
    </p>
    </subsection>
    
    <subsection name="accounts">
    <p>The <strong>accounts</strong> tag declares the accounts from which mail will 
    be fetched by the fetch task. Accounts run concurrently.</p>
    
    <p>The tag has these child tags (minimum cardinality, maximum cardinality):
    <ul>
    <li><strong><a href="#account">account</a></strong> (0, *)</li>
    <li><strong><a href="#alllocal">alllocal</a></strong> (0, 1)</li>
    </ul>
    </p>
    
    <p>
    <source>
    &lt;accounts&gt;
    ...
    &lt;/accounts&gt;
    </source>
    </p>
    </subsection>
    
    <subsection name="blacklist">
    <p>The <strong>blacklist</strong> tag declares a list of recipient addresses 
    for whom mail will be rejected and what happens to the rejected mail.</p>
    
    <p>The tag value is a tab, comma or space delimited list of recipient 
    addresses, eg: <code>wibble@mydomain.com, flobble@mydomain.com</code>.</p>
    
    <p>The tag has these attributes:
    <dl>
    <dt><strong>reject</strong></dt>
    <dd>A boolean. If &quot;true&quot;, mail for recipients in the blacklist will
    not be injected into the James input spool. If &quot;false&quot;, mail for
    recipients in the blacklist will be injected into the James input spool with the
    Mail Attribute <code>org.apache.james.Fetchmail.isBlacklistedRecipient</code>
    added to the mail.</dd>
    <dt><strong>leaveonserver</strong></dt>
    <dd>A boolean. If &quot;true&quot;, mail for recipients in the blacklist will be
    left on the server. If &quot;false&quot;, mail for recipients in the blacklist 
    will be marked for deletion.</dd>
    <dt><strong>markseen</strong></dt>
    <dd>A boolean. If &quot;true&quot;, mail for recipients in the blacklist will be
    marked as seen on the server. If &quot;false&quot;, mail for recipients in the blacklist 
    will not be marked as seen.</dd>
    </dl>
    </p>
    
    <p>
    <source>
    &lt;blacklist 
        reject=&quot;true&quot; 
        leaveonserver=&quot;true&quot;
        markseen=&quot;true&quot;&gt;
    wibble@mydomain.com, flobble@mydomain.com
    &lt;/blacklist&gt;
    </source>
    </p>
    </subsection>
    
    <subsection name="defaultdomain">
    <p>The <strong>defaultdomain</strong> tag declares the domain name to be 
    appended to the <code>From:</code> header of a mail that has a valid user part
    but is missing the domain part.</p>
    
    <p>If not specified, the default behaviour is to append the canonical host name
    of the James server.</p>
    
    <p>The tag value is the name of the server to append. The name must be a server
    declared in the <strong>servernames</strong> tag of the <strong>James</strong>
    block in the configuration or the name <code>localhost</code>.</p>
    
    <p>
    <source>
    &lt;defaultdomain&gt;
        mydomain.com
    &lt;/defaultdomain&gt;
    </source>
    </p>
    </subsection>
    
    <subsection name="fetchall">
    <p>The <strong>fetchall</strong> tag declares if all mail should be fetched from
    the server, or just unseen mail.</p>
    
    <p>The tag value is a boolean. If true, all mail is fetched. If false, only 
    unseen mail is fetched.</p>
    
    <p>
    <source>
    &lt;fetchall&gt;false&lt;/fetchall&gt;
    </source>
    </p>
    </subsection>
    
    <subsection name="fetched">
    <p>The <strong>fetched</strong> tag declares what will happen to mail on the
    external server that is successfully injected into the James input spool.</p>
    
    <p>The tag has these attributes:
    <dl>
    <dt><strong>leaveonserver</strong></dt>
    <dd>A boolean. If &quot;true&quot;, mail injected into the James input spool 
    will be left on the server. If &quot;false&quot;, mail injected into the James
    input spool will be marked for deletion.</dd>
    <dt><strong>markseen</strong></dt>
    <dd>A boolean. If &quot;true&quot;, mail injected into the James input spool 
    will be marked as seen on the server. If &quot;false&quot;, mail injected into
    the James input spool will not be marked as seen.</dd>
    </dl>
    </p>
    
    <p>
    <source>
    &lt;fetched leaveonserver=&quot;true&quot; markseen=&quot;true&quot;/&gt;
    </source>
    </p>
    </subsection>
    
    <subsection name="host">
    <p>The <strong>host</strong> tag declares the IP address of the external
    server from which mail is fetched.</p>
    
    <p>The tag value is the DNS name or IP address literal of the external
    server.</p>
    
    <p>
    <source>
    &lt;host&gt;pop3.server.com&lt;/host&gt;
    </source>
    </p>
    </subsection>
    
    <subsection name="interval">
    <p>The <strong>interval</strong> tag declares the period between invocations of
    the fetch tasks. If a fetch task is still active from a previous invocation
    when the period expires, the new invocation is skipped over.</p>
    
    <p>The tag value is an integer representing the number of milliseconds to elapse
    between invocations of the fetch tasks.</p>
    
    <p>
    <source>
    &lt;interval&gt;60000&lt;/interval&gt;
    </source>
    </p>
    </subsection>
    
    <subsection name="javaMailFolderName">
    <p>The <strong>javaMailFolderName</strong> tag declares the name of the root 
    folder on the external server from which mail is fetched.</p>
    
    <p>The tag value is the cAsE-sEnSiTiVe name of the root folder on the external
    server from which mail is fetched. For POP3 servers this is always 
    <code>INBOX</code>.</p>
    
    <p>
    <source>
    &lt;javaMailFolderName&gt;INBOX&lt;/javaMailFolderName&gt;
    </source>
    </p>
    </subsection>
    
    <subsection name="javaMailProperties">
    <p>The <strong>javaMailProperties</strong> tag declares the properties to be
    applied to the JavaMail Session used by the fetch task. These override the
    properties answered by <code>System.getProperties()</code>. Many JavaMail
    properties are specific to the JavaMail Provider selected by the 
    <a href="#javaMailProviderName">javaMailProviderName</a> tag.</p>
    
    <p><strong>Relying on the default values selected by the Provider can be
    inappropriate.</strong> For instance, the default connection and I/O timeout 
    values of infinite for the default IMAP and POP3 Providers is rarely what is
    required. Consult the documentation of the Provider for details and options.</p>
    
    <p>Documentation for the default Provider for IMAP is located
    <a href="http://java.sun.com/products/javamail/javadocs/com/sun/mail/imap/package-summary.html">
    here</a>.</p>
    
    <p>Documentation for the default Provider for POP3 is located
    <a href="http://java.sun.com/products/javamail/javadocs/com/sun/mail/pop3/package-summary.html">
    here</a>.</p>
    
    <p>Details of how to change a Provider are located
    <a href="http://java.sun.com/products/javamail/javadocs/javax/mail/Session.html">
    here</a>.</p>
    
    <p>The tag has these child tags (minimum cardinality, maximum cardinality):
    <ul>
    <li><strong><a href="#property">property</a></strong> (0, *)</li>
    </ul>
    </p>
    
    <p>
    <source>
    &lt;javaMailProperties&gt;
    ...
    &lt;/javaMailProperties&gt;
    </source>
    </p>
    </subsection>
    
    <subsection name="javaMailProviderName">
    <p>The <strong>javaMailProviderName</strong> tag selects the JavaMail protocol
    Provider used to interact with the external server.</p>
    
    <p>The tag value is the name of a JavaMail supported protocol, such as 
    <code>pop3</code> or <code>imap</code>. The name is used to select the default
    Provider for the protocol.</p>
    
    <p>
    <source>
    &lt;javaMailProviderName&gt;pop3&lt;/javaMailProviderName&gt;
    </source>
    </p>
    </subsection>
    
    <subsection name="maxmessagesize">
    
      <p>The <strong>maxmessagesize</strong> tag declares the maximum permitted message
      size for messages injected into the James input spool and what happens to fetched
      messages that exceed this size.</p>
      <p>The tag has these attributes:
      <dl>
        <dt><strong>limit</strong></dt>
        <dd>An integer. The maximum message size expressed in Kilobytes. If 0, there is
        no limit.</dd>
        <dt><strong>reject</strong></dt>
        <dd>A boolean. If &quot;true&quot;, mail whose message size exceeds the maximum
        permitted size will not be injected into the James input spool. If 
        &quot;false&quot;, mail whose message size exceeds the maximum permitted size will
        have its contents removed, an explanatory error message and the Mail Attribute
        <code>org.apache.james.Fetchmail.isMaxMessageSizeExceeded</code> added prior to 
        injection into the James input spool, (see below for the location of an example).</dd>
        <dt><strong>leaveonserver</strong></dt>
        <dd>A boolean. If &quot;true&quot;, mail whose message size exceeds the maximum
        permitted size will be left on the server. If &quot;false&quot;, mail whose message
        size exceeds the maximum permitted size will be marked for deletion.</dd>
        <dt><strong>markseen</strong></dt>
        <dd>A boolean. If &quot;true&quot;, mail whose message size exceeds the maximum
        permitted size will be marked as seen on the server. If &quot;false&quot;,
        mail whose message size exceeds the maximum permitted size will not be marked as
        seen.</dd>
      </dl>
      
      </p>
      
      <p>
      <source>
      &lt;maxmessagesize 
          limit=&quot;4096&quot;
          reject=&quot;false&quot;
          leaveonserver=&quot;false&quot;
          markseen=&quot;false&quot;/&gt;
      </source>
      </p>
      
      <p>An example configuration using James mailet processing to bounce fetched
      messages that exceed the maximum permitted size can be found in the file
      <code>$PHOENIX_HOME/apps/james/conf/samples/Fetchmail/maxMessageSize.xml</code>.
      </p>
    </subsection>
    
    <subsection name="recipientnotfound">
    <p>The <strong>recipientnotfound</strong> tag declares what happens to mail for
    which a sole intended recipient cannot be found when attempting to determine
    the recipient from the mail headers.</p>
    
    <p>In configurations with more than one account per fetch task, processing of
    matched mail can be deferred to the next run of the fetch task. This gives 
    other accounts that may be able to determine a sole intended recipient an
    opportunity to do so before recipientnotfound processing is invoked.</p>
    
    <p>The tag has these attributes:
    <dl>
    <dt><strong>defer</strong></dt>
    <dd>A boolean. If &quot;true&quot;, mail for which a sole intended recipient 
    cannot be determined is left unprocessed until the next run of the fetch task.
    If &quot;false&quot;, mail for which a sole intended recipient cannot be
    determined is processed immediately.</dd>
    <dt><strong>reject</strong></dt>
    <dd>A boolean. If &quot;true&quot;, mail for which a sole intended recipient 
    cannot be determined will not be injected into the James input spool. If 
    &quot;false&quot;, mail for which a sole intended recipient cannot be 
    determined will be injected into the James input spool using the recipient
    attribute of the current account and with the Mail Attribute 
    <code>org.apache.james.Fetchmail.isRecipientNotFound</code> added to the
    mail.</dd>
    <dt><strong>leaveonserver</strong></dt>
    <dd>A boolean. If &quot;true&quot;, mail for which a sole intended recipient 
    cannot be determined will be left on the server. If &quot;false&quot;, mail for
    which a sole intended recipient cannot be determined will be marked for 
    deletion.</dd>
    <dt><strong>markseen</strong></dt>
    <dd>A boolean. If &quot;true&quot;, mail for which a sole intended recipient 
    cannot be determined will be marked as seen on the server. If &quot;false&quot;,
    mail for which a sole intended recipient cannot be determined will not be marked
    as seen.</dd>
    </dl>
    </p>
    
    <p>
    <source>
    &lt;recipientnotfound 
        defer=&quot;true&quot;
        reject=&quot;true&quot;
        leaveonserver=&quot;true&quot;
        markseen=&quot;true&quot;/&gt;
    </source>
    </p>
    </subsection>
    
    <subsection name="recursesubfolders">
    <p>The <strong>recursesubfolders</strong> tag declares if mail should be fetched 
    from sub-folders of the root folder, or just the root folder.</p>
    
    <p>The tag value is a boolean. If true, mail is fetched from the root folder and
    its subfolders. If false, mail is fetched from just the root folder.</p>
    
    <p>
    <source>
    &lt;recursesubfolders&gt;false&lt;/recursesubfolders&gt;
    </source>
    </p>
    </subsection>
    
    <subsection name="remoteReceivedHeader">
    <p>The <strong>remoteReceivedHeader</strong> tag declares the zero based
    index of the RFC2822 compliant RECEIVED header used to determine the address and
    host name of the remote MTA that sent a fetched message and what happens to 
    messages when the specified header is invalid.</p>
    
    <p>Typically, the first (index = 0) RECEIVED header is for the local MTA that 
    delivered the message to the message store and the second (index = 1) RECEIVED
    header is for the remote MTA that delivered the message to the local MTA. When
    this configuration applies, the <strong>remoteReceivedHeaderIndex</strong> should
    be set to <strong>1</strong>.
    </p>
    
    <p>To verify the correct setting, examine the RECEIVED headers for messages
    delivered to the configured message store and locate the first one containing a
    remote domain in the'from' field. Remembering that zero based indexing is used,
    if this the second header, use an index of 1, if this is the third header, use an
    index of 2, and so forth.</p>
    
    <p>Matchers such as InSpammerBlacklist use the remote address and/or remote host
    name to identify illegitimate remote MTAs. If you do not use such matchers, the
    <strong>remoteReceivedHeaderIndex</strong> tag may be omitted or the default
    index value of -1 can be specified. This causes the remote address to be set to
    <code>127.0.0.1</code> and the remote host name to be set to
    <code>localhost</code>. Matchers almost always considered these values to be
    legitimate.</p>
    
    <p>The tag has these attributes:
    <dl>
    <dt><strong>index</strong></dt>
    <dd>An integer whose meaning is described above.
    </dd>
    <dt><strong>reject</strong></dt>
    <dd>A boolean. If &quot;true&quot;, mail whose specified recieved header is invalid
    will not be injected into the James input spool. If &quot;false&quot;, mail whose 
    specified recieved header is invalid will be injected into the James input spool with 
    the Mail Attribute <code>org.apache.james.Fetchmail.isInvalidReceivedHeader</code>
    added to the mail, the remote address set to <code>127.0.0.1</code> and the remote 
    host name set to <code>localhost</code>.
    </dd>
    <dt><strong>leaveonserver</strong></dt>
    <dd>A boolean. If &quot;true&quot;, mail whose specified recieved header is invalid
    will be left on the server. If &quot;false&quot;, mail whose specified recieved header
    is invalid will be marked for deletion.</dd>
    <dt><strong>markseen</strong></dt>
    <dd>A boolean. If &quot;true&quot;, mail whose specified recieved header is invalid
    will be marked as seen on the server. If &quot;false&quot;, mail whose specified
    recieved header is invalid will not be marked as seen.</dd>
    </dl>
    </p>
    
    <p>
    <source>
    &lt;remoteReceivedHeader
        index=&quot;1&quot; 
        reject=&quot;true&quot;
        leaveonserver=&quot;true&quot;
        markseen=&quot;true&quot;/&gt;
    </source>
    </p>
    
    <p>An example configuration using James mailet processing to notify the postmaster
    of fetched messages that contain an invalid Received header can be found in the file
    <code>$PHOENIX_HOME/apps/james/conf/samples/Fetchmail/remoteReceivedHeader.xml</code>.
    </p>
    </subsection>
    
    <subsection name="remoterecipient">
    <p>The <strong>remoterecipient</strong> tag declares what happens to mail for
    which the domain part of the recipient is remote. A domain is remote if it is 
    not a server declared in the <strong>servernames</strong> tag of the
    <strong>James</strong> block in the configuration.</p>
    
    <p>The tag has these attributes:
    <dl>
    <dt><strong>reject</strong></dt>
    <dd>A boolean. If &quot;true&quot;, mail for remote recipients will not be 
    injected into the James input spool. If &quot;false&quot;, mail for remote
    recipients will be injected into the James input spool with the Mail Attribute 
    <code>org.apache.james.Fetchmail.isRemoteRecipient</code> added to the mail.
    </dd>
    <dt><strong>leaveonserver</strong></dt>
    <dd>A boolean. If &quot;true&quot;, mail for remote recipients will be left on
    the server. If &quot;false&quot;, mail for remote recipients will be marked for 
    deletion.</dd>
    <dt><strong>markseen</strong></dt>
    <dd>A boolean. If &quot;true&quot;, mail for remote recipients will be marked as
    seen on the server. If &quot;false&quot;, mail for remote recipients will not be
    marked as seen.</dd>
    </dl>
    </p>
    
    <p>
    <source>
    &lt;remoterecipient 
        reject=&quot;true&quot;
        leaveonserver=&quot;true&quot;
        markseen=&quot;true&quot;/&gt;
    </source>
    </p>
    </subsection>
    
    <subsection name="undeliverable">
    <p>The <strong>undeliverable</strong> tag declares what happens to mail that
    cannot be delivered.</p>
    
    <p>The tag has these attributes:
    <dl>
    <dt><strong>leaveonserver</strong></dt>
    <dd>A boolean. If &quot;true&quot;, mail that cannot be delivered will be left
    on the server. If &quot;false&quot;, mail that cannot be delivered will be
    marked for deletion.</dd>
    <dt><strong>markseen</strong></dt>
    <dd>A boolean. If &quot;true&quot;, mail for that cannot be delivered will be
    marked as seen on the server. If &quot;false&quot;, mail that cannot be
    delivered will not be marked as seen.</dd>
    </dl>
    </p>
    
    <p>
    <source>
    &lt;undeliverable
        leaveonserver=&quot;true&quot;
        markseen=&quot;true&quot;/&gt;
    </source>
    </p>
    </subsection>
    
    <subsection name="userundefined">
    <p>The <strong>userundefined</strong> tag declares what happens to mail for
    which the recipient is not defined as a James user.</p>
    
    <p>The tag has these attributes:
    <dl>
    <dt><strong>reject</strong></dt>
    <dd>A boolean. If &quot;true&quot;, mail for recipients who are not defined as
    James users will not be injected into the James input spool. If 
    &quot;false&quot;, mail for recipients who are not defined as James users will
    be injected into the James input spool with the Mail Attribute 
    <code>org.apache.james.Fetchmail.isUserUndefined</code> added to the mail.
    </dd>
    <dt><strong>leaveonserver</strong></dt>
    <dd>A boolean. If &quot;true&quot;, mail for recipients who are not defined as
    James users will be left on the server. If &quot;false&quot;, mail for 
    recipients who are not defined as James users will be marked for deletion.</dd>
    <dt><strong>markseen</strong></dt>
    <dd>A boolean. If &quot;true&quot;, mail for recipients who are not defined as
    James users will be marked as seen on the server. If &quot;false&quot;, mail
    for recipients who are not defined as James users will not be marked as seen.
    </dd>
    </dl>
    </p>
    
    <p>
    <source>
    &lt;userundefined
        reject=&quot;true&quot;
        leaveonserver=&quot;true&quot;
        markseen=&quot;true&quot;/&gt;
    </source>
    </p>
    </subsection>
    
    <subsection name="account">
    <p>The <strong>account</strong> tag declares an account on the external server
    from which mail should be fetched.</p>
    
    <p>The tag has these attributes:
    <dl>
    <dt><strong>user</strong></dt>
    <dd>The string to be passed as the user when connecting to the external server.
    </dd>
    <dt><strong>password</strong></dt>
    <dd>The string to be passed as the password when connecting to the external 
    server.</dd>
    <dt><strong>recipient</strong></dt>
    <dd>The recipient to whom messages will be delivered when the intended recipient
    cannot be determined or when the intended recipient is to be ignored.</dd>
    <dt><strong>ignorercpt-header</strong></dt>
    <dd>A boolean. If &quot;true&quot;, mail is always delivered to the recipient
    declared in the <strong>recipient</strong> attribute above. If 
    &quot;false&quot;, the intended recipient is determined from the mail headers or
    the process declared by the <strong>recipientnotfound</strong> tag.
    </dd>
    </dl>
    </p>
    
    <p>
    <source>
    &lt;account
        user=&quot;myaccount&quot;
        password=&quot;mypassword&quot;
        recipient=&quot;user@localhost&quot;
        ignorercpt-header=&quot;true&quot;/&gt;
    </source>
    </p>
    </subsection>
    
    <subsection name="alllocal">
    <p>The <strong>alllocal</strong> tag declares the parameters to be applied to
    dynamic accounts. The set of dynamic accounts is refreshed each time the fetch
    task runs by combining the <strong>alllocal</strong> tag attributes with each of
    the currently defined James users to create an account for every James user.</p>
    
    <p>The tag has these attributes:
    <dl>
    <dt><strong>userprefix</strong></dt>
    <dd>The string to be added before the James user when constructing the string
    passed as the user when connecting to the external server.
    </dd>
    <dt><strong>usersuffix</strong></dt>
    <dd>The string to be added after the James user when constructing the string
    passed as the user when connecting to the external server.
    </dd>
    <dt><strong>password</strong></dt>
    <dd>The string to be passed as the password when connecting to the external 
    server.</dd>
    <dt><strong>recipientprefix</strong></dt>
    <dd>The string to be added before the James user when constructing the recipient
    to whom messages will be delivered when the intended recipient cannot be 
    determined or when the intended recipient is to be ignored.</dd>
    <dt><strong>recipientsuffix</strong></dt>
    <dd>The string to be added after the James user when constructing the recipient
    to whom messages will be delivered when the intended recipient cannot be 
    determined or when the intended recipient is to be ignored.</dd>
    <dt><strong>ignorercpt-header</strong></dt>
    <dd>A boolean. If &quot;true&quot;, mail is always delivered to the recipient
    constructed from the <strong>recipientprefix</strong> and 
    <strong>recipientsuffix</strong> attributes above and the James user. If 
    &quot;false&quot;, the intended recipient is determined from the mail headers or
    the process declared by the <strong>recipientnotfound</strong> tag.
    </dd>
    </dl>
    </p>
    
    <p>
    <source>
    &lt;alllocal
        userprefix=&quot;&quot;
        usersuffix=&quot;@external.domain.com&quot;
        password=&quot;mypassword&quot;
        recipientprefix=&quot;&quot;
        recipientsuffix=&quot;@mydomain.com&quot;
        ignorercpt-header=&quot;true&quot;/&gt;
    </source>
    </p>
    </subsection>
    
    <subsection name="property">
    <p>The <strong>property</strong> tag declares a name/value pair.</p>
    
    <p>The tag has these attributes:
    <dl>
    <dt><strong>name</strong></dt>
    <dd>The name of the property.
    </dd>
    <dt><strong>value</strong></dt>
    <dd>The value of the property.</dd>
    </dl>
    </p>
    
    <p>
    <source>
    &lt;property
        name=&quot;mail.pop3.connectiontimeout&quot;
        value=&quot;180000&quot;/&gt;
    </source>
    </p>
    </subsection>
  
  </section>
  
  <section name="Fetchmail Examples">
  
    <p>Full sources to the examples discussed below can be found in the directory
    <code>$PHOENIX_HOME/apps/james/conf/samples/Fetchmail</code>.</p>
    
    <subsection name="One Account, One User">
    <p>When all mail for an account is to be delivered to a single user, 
    configure each account to ignore the recipient in the mail headers and deliver
    to the specified recipient. The <strong>accounts</strong> block looks like 
    this:</p>
    
    <p>
    <source>
    &lt;accounts&gt;
        &lt;account
            user=&quot;user1@external.domain.com&quot;
            password=&quot;password1&quot;
            recipient=&quot;user1@localhost&quot;
            ignorercpt-header=&quot;true&quot;/&gt;
    
        &lt;account
            user=&quot;user2@external.domain.com&quot;
            password=&quot;password2&quot;
            recipient=&quot;user2@localhost&quot;
            ignorercpt-header=&quot;true&quot;/&gt;
    
        &lt;account
            user=&quot;user3@external.domain.com&quot;
            password=&quot;password3&quot;
            recipient=&quot;user3@localhost&quot;
            ignorercpt-header=&quot;true&quot;/&gt;
    &lt;/accounts&gt;
    </source>
    </p>
    </subsection>
    
    <subsection name="One Account, Many Users">
    <p>When an account contains mail to be delivered to many users, configure each
    account to determine the recipient from the mail headers and deliver to that 
    user. The <strong>accounts</strong> block looks like this:</p>
    
    <p>
    <source>
    &lt;accounts&gt;
        &lt;account
            user=&quot;global@external.domain.com&quot;
            password=&quot;password&quot;
            recipient=&quot;Fetchmail@localhost&quot;
            ignorercpt-header=&quot;false&quot;/&gt;
    &lt;/accounts&gt;
    </source>
    </p>
    
    <p>The <strong>recipientnotfound</strong> tag is used to declare what happens 
    when the recipient cannot be determined from the mail headers. In the example 
    below, mail is injected into the spool using the recipient declared in the
    <strong>account</strong> tag:</p>
    
    <p>
    <source>
    &lt;recipientnotfound
        defer=&quot;false&quot;
        reject=&quot;false&quot;
        leaveonserver=&quot;false&quot;
        markseen=&quot;false&quot;/&gt;
    </source>
    </p>
    </subsection>
    
    <subsection name="One Account, One User - Dynamic">
    <p>When an external server supports virtual mailboxes, Fetchmail's dynamic 
    account facility can be used. This greatly simplifies user configuration as 
    the Fetchmail accounts for users are automatically synchronized with those
    defined in the James user repository. This guarantees that mail for all local 
    users will be fetched and delivered.</p>
    
    <p>Currently, there is a limitation that all virtual accounts and the global
    account must share the same password.</p>
    
    <p>The <strong>alllocal</strong> tag declares the parameters for the dynamic 
    accounts. The <strong>accounts</strong> block below will deliver mail for 
    <code>user1@external.domain.com</code> to <code>user1@localhost</code>, 
    <code>user2@external.domain.com</code> to <code>user2@localhost</code>,
    <code>userZ@external.domain.com</code> to <code>userZ@localhost</code> etc.:</p>
    
    <p>
    <source>
    &lt;accounts&gt;
        &lt;alllocal
            userprefix=&quot;&quot;
            usersuffix=&quot;@external.domain.com&quot;
            password=&quot;mypassword&quot;
            recipientprefix=&quot;&quot;
            recipientsuffix=&quot;@localhost&quot;
            ignorercpt-header=&quot;true&quot;/&gt;
    &lt;/accounts&gt;
    </source>
    </p>
    </subsection>
    
    <subsection name="One Account, Many Users - Dynamic">
    
    <p>The <a href="#One Account, One User - Dynamic">One Account, One User - Dynamic</a>
    example guarantees delivery of mail for all local users, but leaves other mail
    on the external server unprocessed. The 
    <a href="#One Account, Many Users">One Account, Many Users</a> example
    processes all mail on the external server, but cannot guarantee delivery to the
    intended recipient. By combining the two, it is possible to guarantee the 
    delivery of mail for all local users and process all mail.</p>
    
    <p>In the snippet below, the <strong>alllocal</strong> tag declares dynamic
    accounts for all local users and the <strong>account</strong> tag configures an
    account to fetch all mail.</p>
    
    <p>The <strong>recipientnotfound</strong> tag rejects mail for which a recipient
    cannot be determined. By the time this processing is activated, the dynamic 
    accounts will have processed mail for all local users, so the mail can 
    only be mail for non-local users or newly arrived mail for local users. It is 
    not possible to know which, but we want to leave mail for local users to be
    dealt with by the dynamic accounts. The next time the dynamic accounts run any
    newly arrived mail for local users will be processed. The remainder will be for
    non-local users and can now be safely dealt with.</p>
    
    <p>The <code>&lt;recipientnotfound defer=&quot;true&quot;</code> attribute 
    enables deferal of the processing of messages for which the recipient cannot be
    determined to the next iteration of the fetch task, and is used here. The 
    relevant tags are:</p>
    
    <p>
    <source>
    &lt;accounts&gt;
        &lt;alllocal
            userprefix=&quot;&quot;
            usersuffix=&quot;@external.domain.com&quot;
            password=&quot;mypassword&quot;
            recipientprefix=&quot;&quot;
            recipientsuffix=&quot;@localhost&quot;
            ignorercpt-header=&quot;true&quot;/&gt;
    
        &lt;account
            user=&quot;global@external.domain.com&quot;
            password=&quot;password&quot;
            recipient=&quot;Fetchmail@localhost&quot;
            ignorercpt-header=&quot;false&quot;/&gt;
    &lt;/accounts&gt;
    
    &lt;recipientnotfound
        defer=&quot;true&quot;
        reject=&quot;true&quot;
        leaveonserver=&quot;true&quot;
        markseen=&quot;true&quot;/&gt;
    </source>
    </p>
    </subsection>
  
  </section>
  
  <section name="Fetchmail Caveats">
  
    <p>These are some things to be aware of when using Fetchmail:
    
    <ul>
    
      <li>As noted in the
      <a href="#One Account, One User - Dynamic">One Account, One User - Dynamic</a>
      example, all virtual accounts and the global account must share the same 
      password. A future version might associate each James user to a set of account
      credentials.</li>
      
      <li>When using dynamic accounts, an account is generated and an attempt made to
      fetch mail for all James users defined to James even if there is no such mailbox
      on the server. This is inefficient but not fatal. The solution is the same as 
      described above.</li>
      
      <li>When using dynamic accounts, as described in the
      <a href="#One Account, Many Users - Dynamic">One Account, Many Users - Dynamic</a>
      example, the user name used to fetch the mail for all accounts must not be
      defined as a James user. If it is, a dynamic account will be generated for it
      and fetch all the mail before the account declared to process mail for all users
      has an opportunity to run!</li>
      
      <li>The now deprecated fetchPOP interacted with the <code>FetchedFrom</code> 
      matcher to detect mail injected by fetchPOP. This will not work with Fetchmail. 
      Compared to fetchPOP, there are far fewer occasions when mail injected by 
      Fetchmail requires special processing. When it does, use the HasMailAttribute 
      matcher to match the attribute named 
      <code>org.apache.james.Fetchmail.taskName</code> to detect all mail injected by
      Fetchmail. To detect mail injected by a specific fetch task, use one of the 
      HasMailAttributeWithValue matchers to match on the attribute name and the
      attribute value. The attribute value is the name of the fetch task that 
      injected the mail.</li>
      
      <li>The POP3 protocol does not enforce support of any of the Flags associated 
      with messages other than DELETED. This means that 
      <code>markseen=&quot;true&quot;</code> will most likely have no effect and 
      therefore, the <strong>fetchall</strong> tag will be inoperative. In this 
      situation, the only way to avoid repeatedly fetching the same mail is to delete
      it from the server using <code>leaveonserver=&quot;false&quot;/&gt;</code>.</li>
      
      <li>If using a Exchange 2000 or Exchange 2003 server get sure you fix the CLRF bug. 
      See <a href="http://support.microsoft.com/kb/816896/en-us"> Bug description and fix</a></li>
    </ul>

    </p>

  </section>

  <section name="Fetchmail Gmail">
  
    <p>Use this configuration to fetch Gmail via POP3. Please don't forget to enable POP3 in Gmail (<a href="http://mail.google.com/support/bin/answer.py?answer=13273">read how-to</a>).</p>
  
    <source>
&lt;fetchmail enabled=&quot;true&quot;&gt;
&lt;fetch name=&quot;gmail.com&quot;&gt;
&lt;accounts&gt;
&lt;account user=&quot;YOUR_USER@gmail.com&quot; password=&quot;YOUR_PASSWORD&quot; recipient=&quot;YOUR_EMAIL_ADDRESS_IN_JAMES&quot; ignorercpt-header=&quot;true&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/accounts&gt;
&lt;host&gt;pop.gmail.com&lt;/host&gt;
&lt;interval&gt;600000&lt;/interval&gt;
&lt;javaMailProviderName&gt;pop3&lt;/javaMailProviderName&gt;
&lt;javaMailFolderName&gt;INBOX&lt;/javaMailFolderName&gt;
&lt;javaMailProperties&gt;
&lt;property name=&quot;mail.pop3.ssl.enable&quot; value=&quot;true&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/javaMailProperties&gt;
&lt;fetchall&gt;false&lt;/fetchall&gt;
&lt;recursesubfolders&gt;false&lt;/recursesubfolders&gt;
&lt;defaultdomain&gt;localhost&lt;/defaultdomain&gt;
&lt;fetched leaveonserver=&quot;true&quot; markseen=&quot;true&quot;/&gt;
&lt;remotereceivedheader index=&quot;1&quot; reject=&quot;true&quot; leaveonserver=&quot;true&quot; markseen=&quot;false&quot;/&gt;
&lt;maxmessagesize limit=&quot;0&quot; reject=&quot;false&quot; leaveonserver=&quot;true&quot; markseen=&quot;false&quot;/&gt;
&lt;undeliverable leaveonserver=&quot;true&quot; markseen=&quot;false&quot;/&gt;
&lt;recipientnotfound defer=&quot;true&quot; reject=&quot;true&quot; leaveonserver=&quot;true&quot; markseen=&quot;false&quot;/&gt;
&lt;blacklist reject=&quot;true&quot; leaveonserver=&quot;true&quot; markseen=&quot;false&quot;&gt; wibble@localhost, flobble@localhost&lt;/blacklist&gt;
&lt;userundefined reject=&quot;true&quot; leaveonserver=&quot;true&quot; markseen=&quot;false&quot; /&gt;
&lt;remoterecipient reject=&quot;true&quot; leaveonserver=&quot;true&quot; markseen=&quot;false&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/fetch&gt;
&lt;/fetchmail&gt;
    </source>
  
    <p>Use this configuration to fetch Gmail via IMAP4. Please don't forget to enable IMAP4 in Gmail (<a href="http://mail.google.com/support/bin/answer.py?answer=77695">read how-to</a>).</p>
  
    <source>
&lt;fetchmail enabled=&quot;true&quot;&gt;
&lt;fetch name=&quot;gmail.com&quot;&gt;
&lt;accounts&gt;
&lt;account user=&quot;YOUR_USER@gmail.com&quot; password=&quot;YOUR_PASSWORD&quot; recipient=&quot;YOUR_EMAIL_ADDRESS_IN_JAMES&quot; ignorercpt-header=&quot;true"/&gt;
&lt;/accounts&gt;
&lt;host&gt;imap.gmail.com&lt;/host&gt;
&lt;interval&gt;600000&lt;/interval&gt;
&lt;javaMailProviderName&gt;imap&lt;/javaMailProviderName&gt;
&lt;javaMailFolderName&gt;INBOX&lt;/javaMailFolderName&gt;
&lt;javaMailProperties&gt;
&lt;property name=&quot;mail.imap.ssl.enable&quot; value=&quot;true&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/javaMailProperties&gt;
&lt;fetchall&gt;false&lt;/fetchall&gt;
&lt;recursesubfolders&gt;false&lt;/recursesubfolders&gt;
&lt;defaultdomain&gt;localhost&lt;/defaultdomain&gt;
&lt;fetched leaveonserver=&quot;true&quot; markseen=&quot;true&quot;/&gt;
&lt;remotereceivedheader index=&quot;1&quot; reject=&quot;true&quot; leaveonserver=&quot;true&quot; markseen=&quot;false&quot;/&gt;
&lt;maxmessagesize limit=&quot;0&quot; reject=&quot;false&quot; leaveonserver=&quot;true&quot; markseen=&quot;false&quot;/&gt;
&lt;undeliverable leaveonserver=&quot;true&quot; markseen=&quot;false&quot;/&gt;
&lt;recipientnotfound defer=&quot;true&quot; reject=&quot;true&quot; leaveonserver=&quot;true&quot; markseen=&quot;false&quot;/&gt;
&lt;blacklist reject=&quot;true&quot; leaveonserver=&quot;true&quot; markseen=&quot;false&quot;&gt; wibble@localhost, flobble@localhost&lt;/blacklist&gt;
&lt;userundefined reject=&quot;true&quot; leaveonserver=&quot;true&quot; markseen=&quot;false&quot; /&gt;
&lt;remoterecipient reject=&quot;true&quot; leaveonserver=&quot;true&quot; markseen=&quot;false&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/fetch&gt;
&lt;/fetchmail&gt;
    </source>
  
  </section>

</body>

</document>
