<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
  or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
  distributed with this work for additional information
  regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
  to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
  "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
  with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
  software distributed under the License is distributed on an
  "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
  KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
  specific language governing permissions and limitations
  under the License.    
-->
<document>

 <properties>
  <title>Apache James Server 3 - Mailet API</title>
 </properties>

<body>

  <section name="MailetContainer">
  
    <subsection name="Introduction">
    
      <p>James separates the services that deliver mail to James (i.e. SMTP, FetchMail) 
         from the engine that processes mail after it is received by James.  The 
         SpoolManager component is James' mail processing engine.  James' SpoolManager component 
         is also called the Mailet container. It is these mailets and matchers that actually carry out mail processing.</p>
      
      <p>More on the configuration of the SpoolManager and the Mailet API can be found <a href="config-mailetcontainer.html">here</a>.</p>
      
    </subsection>
    
    <subsection name="Matchers and Mailets">
    
      <p>Core to the SpoolManager operation are Matchers and Mailets.  A Matcher is a 
      simple object that checks whether a mail message matches a particular condition. 
      A mailet is another type object that processes an email message in some way.  Some 
      typical tasks appropriate for a mailet would be adding a header, delivering the message 
      to a local repository, or handling remote delivery.  Both the Matcher and Mailet APIs are 
      public, allowing James users to write their own custom matchers and mailets.  James 
      comes with a large set of pre-built matchers and mailets.</p>

      <p>Matchers and mailets are used in pairs.  At each stage in processing a message is checked
      against a matcher.  The matcher will attempt to match the mail message.  The match is not simply
      a yes or no issue.  Instead, the match method returns a collection of matched recipients.  If the
      this collection of matched recipients is empty, the mailet is not invoked.  If the collection of
      matched recipients is the entire set of original recipients, the mail is then processed by the
      associated mailet.  Finally, if the matcher only matches a proper subset of the original recipients,
      the original mail is duplicated.  The recipients for one message are set to the matched recipients,
      and that message is processed by the mailet.  The recipients for the other mail are set to the
      non-matching recipients, and that message is not processed by the mailet.</p>

        <p>Note that you can specify per mailet and per matcher specific <a href="config-mailetcontainer.html#Error_handling">error handling logic.</a></p>
    
    </subsection>

    <subsection name="Processors">

      <p>One level up from the matchers and mailets are the processors.  Each processor 
      is a list of matcher/mailet pairs.  During mail processing, mail messages will be 
      processed by each pair, in order.  In most cases, the message will be processed by 
      all the pairs in the processor.  However, it is possible for a mailet to change the 
      state of the mail message so it is immediately directed to another processor, and no 
      additional processing occurs in the current processor.  Typically this occurs when the mailet 
      wants to prevent future processing of this message (i.e. the mail message has been delivered locally, 
      and hence requires no further processing) or when the mail message has been identified
      as a candidate for special processing (i.e. the message is spam and thus should be 
      routed to the spam processor).  Because of this redirection, the processors in the 
      SpoolManager form a tree.  The root processor, which must be present, is the root of
      this tree.</p>
    
    </subsection>
        
    <subsection name="SpoolManager">

      <p>The SpoolManager continually checks for mail in the spool repository.  When
      mail is first found in the repository, it is delivered to the root processor.  
      Mail can be placed on this spool from a number of sources (SMTP, FetchPOP, a 
      custom component).  This spool repository is also used for storage of mail that is
      being redirected from one processor to another.  Mail messages are driven through 
      the processor tree until they reach the end of a processor or are marked completed 
      by a mailet.</p>
    
      <p>More on configuration of the SpoolManager can be found <a href="config-mailetcontainer.html">here</a>.</p>
    
      <p>Much of the power of James lies in the SpoolManager component.  <a href="dev-extend-matcher.html">Custom matchers</a> and
      <a href="dev-extend-mailet.html">custom mailets</a> can be easily developed to address an administrator's particular needs.  The
      processor tree can easily be configured to sort, filter, and deliver mail based on any 
      number of criteria.  Mail administrators new to James should spend some time learning how 
      to configure the SpoolManager to meet their needs.</p>
 
     </subsection>
  
     <subsection name="Mailet API">
    
        <p>The Mailet API is a simple API used to build mail processing applications.  James is a Mailet 
        container, allowing administrators to deploy Mailets (both custom and pre-made) to carry out a 
        variety of complex mail processing tasks.  In the default configuration James uses Mailets to carry 
        out a number of tasks that are carried out deep in the source code of other mail servers (i.e. list 
        processing, remote and local delivery).</p>
    
        <p>As it stands today, the Mailet API defines interfaces for both Matchers and Mailets.</p>
    
        <ul>
          <li>Matchers, as their name would suggest, match mail messages against certain conditions.  They 
              return some subset (possibly the entire set) of the original recipients of the message if there 
              is a match.  An inherent part of the Matcher contract is that a Matcher should not induce any changes
              in a message under evaluation.</li>
          <li>Mailets are responsible for actually processing the message.  They may alter the message in any fashion,
              or pass the message to an external API or component.  This can include delivering a message to its destination 
              repository or SMTP server.</li>
        </ul>
    
        <p>The Mailet API is currently in its second revision.  Although, the Mailet API is expected to undergo substantial changes in the near future, it is our aim that existing Mailets that abided purely by the prior Mailet API interfaces will continue to run with the revised specification.</p>
    
        <p>The Javadoc for the Mailet API can be found <a href="http://james.apache.org/mailet/api/apidocs/">here</a>.</p>

        <p>James bundles a number of Matchers and Mailets in its distribution. You can retrieve the full list of mailets
            and matchers packaged in James <a href="dev-provided-mailets.html">here</a></p>

        <p>You can read more on mailets on following web sites:</p>
    
        <ul>
          <li><a href="http://james.apache.org/mailet/index.html">Mailet Site</a></li>
          <li><a href="http://james.apache.org/mailet/api/index.html">Mailet API</a></li>
          <li><a href="http://james.apache.org/mailet/base/index.html">Mailet Toolkit</a></li>
          <li><a href="http://james.apache.org/mailet/crypto/index.html">Mailet Crypto</a></li>
          <li><a href="http://james.apache.org/mailet/standard/index.html">Mailet Standard</a></li>
        </ul>
    
     </subsection>

  </section>
  
</body>

</document>
