<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
  or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
  distributed with this work for additional information
  regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
  to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
  "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
  with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
  software distributed under the License is distributed on an
  "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
  KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
  specific language governing permissions and limitations
  under the License.    
-->
<document>

 <properties>
  <title>Apache James Server 3 - Feature - Servers</title>
 </properties>

<body>

  <section name="Servers">
  
    <subsection name="Introduction">
    
      <p>Apache James is an open source project intended to produce a robust, flexible, and powerful 
      enterprise class server that provides email and email-related services.  It is also designed to
      be highly customizable, allowing administrators to configure Apache James to process email in a 
      nearly endless variety of fashions.</p>
      
      <p>The standard Apache James distribution deploys inside the Spring dependency injection container.
      In addition to providing a robust server architecture for James, the use of Spring allows Apache James administrators 
      to deploy their own applications inside the container.  These applications can then be accessed during 
      mail processing.</p>
      
      <p>The Apache James Server is implemented as a complete collection of servers and related components that, taken together,
      provide an email solution.  These components are described below.</p>

      <p>Note that each protocol can specify its TLS settings and keys in an independent way.</p>
  
    </subsection>
    
    <subsection name="SMTP Protocol">
    
      <p>SMTP (Simple Mail Transport Protocol) is the standard method of sending and delivering 
      email on the internet. Apache James provides a full-function implementation of the SMTP specification,
      with support for some optional features such as message size limits, SMTP auth, and encrypted 
      client/server communication.</p>
      
      <p>More information on configuring the SMTP service can be found <a href="config-smtp-lmtp.html">here</a>.</p>

      <p>You can find further information about supported protocols and RFCs
        <a href="http://james.apache.org/protocols/smtp.html">on the JAMES-PROTOCOLS project SMTP page</a>
      </p>
    </subsection>
    
    <subsection name="IMAP4 Protocol">
    
      <p>The IMAP4 protocol allows users to retrieve email messages.  It is the method
      most commonly used by email clients to download and manage email messages.</p>
      
      <p>The Apache James version of the IMAP4 service is a simple and straightforward implementation that 
      provides full compliance with the specification and maximum compatibility with common
      IMAP4 clients.  In addition, Apache James can be configured to require SSL/TLS connections for
      IMAP4 client connecting to the server.</p>
      
      <p>More information on configuring the IMAP4 service can be found <a href="config-imap4.html">here</a>.</p>

      <p>You can find further information about supported protocols and RFCs
        <a href="http://james.apache.org/protocols/imap4.html">on the JAMES-PROTOCOLS project IMAP4 page</a>
      </p>

      <p>
        Note that MOVE extension (RFC-6851) needs a MailboxManager implementing the move function. For now, this is only done with
        the CassandraMailboxManager
      </p>
      <p>
        It supports the METADATA extension (RFC-5464):
        <ul>
          <li>
            It does not support the server's metadata so far.
          </li>
          <li>
            It does not support permission on metadata because the ACL extension is not present.
          </li>
          <li>
            The quota limitations on MailboxAnnotations are hardcoded. They concern the number of annotations per mailbox (10), as well as the size of an annotation (1024 bytes)
          </li>
        </ul>
      </p>
    </subsection>
    
    <subsection name="POP3 Protocol">
    
      <p>The POP3 protocol allows users to retrieve email messages.  It is the method
      most commonly used by email clients to download and manage email messages.</p>
      
      <p>The Apache James version of the POP3 service is a simple and straightforward implementation that 
      provides full compliance with the specification and maximum compatibility with common
      POP3 clients.  In addition, Apache James can be configured to require SSL/TLS connections for
      POP3 client connecting to the server.</p>
      
      <p>More information on configuring the POP3 service can be found <a href="config-pop3.html">here</a>.</p>

      <p>You can find further information about supported protocols and RFCs
        <a href="http://james.apache.org/protocols/pop3.html">on the JAMES-PROTOCOLS project POP3 page</a>
      </p>
    </subsection>
    
    <subsection name="FetchMail">
    
      <p>FetchMail, unlike the other Apache James components, is not an implementation of an RFC.  Instead, it's a 
      component that allows the administrator to configure Apache James to retrieve email from a number of POP3 
      servers and deliver them to the local spool.  This is useful for consolidating mail delivered to a
      number of accounts on different machines to a single account.</p>
      
      <p>More information on configuring FetchMail can be found <a href="config-fetchmail.html">here</a>.</p>

    </subsection>
    
    <subsection name="JMX">
    
      <p>JMX (Java Management Extension) is used for the management.</p>
  
    </subsection>  

  </section>
  
</body>

</document>
