<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
  or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
  distributed with this work for additional information
  regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
  to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
  "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
  with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
  software distributed under the License is distributed on an
  "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
  KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
  specific language governing permissions and limitations
  under the License.    
-->
<document>

 <properties>
  <title>James 2.1 - Adding Users</title>
 </properties>

<body>
<section name="Creating User Accounts">
<p>User accounts are shared across services.  A common user repository is shared across James 
services.  That is, once you've created a POP3 mail account and set a password, that same 
account is available for authenticated SMTP and NNTP.</p>
<subsection name="Before You Add Accounts">
<p>In James, user accounts are created throught the RemoteManager.  So, after installation is complete, the first step to adding users 
is to configure the RemoteManager.  More information on RemoteManager configuration can be found 
<a href="remotemanager_configuration_2_1.html">here</a>.  You will need to have configured at least one administrator account and 
ensured that the RemoteManager is enabled.</p>
<p>Also, you need to make sure that your user repository configuration is correct before adding any users.  If 
you change your user repository type (i.e. file to database) or the configuration of your user repository 
(i.e. the file or database URL) after you have added users, you may lose your user data.  Please change these 
values with care.</p>
<p>After you've done this, restart James to ensure that any changes you've made in the configuration are incorporated into 
the running system.  You are now ready to create user accounts.</p>
</subsection>
<p>Once James is up and listening, adding a user is simple:</p>
1.  Telnet to the host and port on which the RemoteManager is listening.  For command-line telnet clients 
this is generally done by typing "telnet &lt;host&gt; &lt;pass&gt;" where &lt;host&gt; is the James 
hostname and &lt;port&gt; is the RemoteManager port specified in the James config.xml.<br/><br/>
2.  You will be prompted for your administrator userid and password.  Enter the values you specified 
in the James config.xml.<br/><br/>
3.  After logging in, type "adduser &lt;user&gt; &lt;password&gt;" where &lt;user&gt; is the user name 
and &lt;password&gt; is the password of the account you wish to create.  Please note that the user name 
should NOT be a complete email address.  Rather, all email addresses of the form &lt;user&gt;@&lt;domain&gt; 
(where &lt;domain&gt; is any of the values specified in the &lt;servernames&gt; block) will be delivered to 
this account by default.  Mailet configuration can change this default behavior.<br/><br/>
4.  Repeat step 3 for all user accounts you wish to create.
<p>That's it.  Your user accounts are now created and can be used by all James services.</p>
</section>
</body>
</document>
