<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
  or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
  distributed with this work for additional information
  regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
  to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
  "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
  with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
  software distributed under the License is distributed on an
  "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
  KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
  specific language governing permissions and limitations
  under the License.    
-->

<document>

 <properties>
  <title>Overview</title>
  <author email="server-dev@james.apache.org">Mail Protocol Tester</author>
 </properties>

<body>
<section name="What is the Apache James MPT?">
<p>
Apache James Mail Protocol Tester (MPT) is a library providing a framework for the 
scritable functional testing of ASCII based line protocols.</p>
<p>
This contains a lightweight scripting framework suitable for the
functional testing of the ASCII line based protocols common in mail.
A script contains a list of client requests and templated server
responses. The framework runs the client lines against a host system
and then compares the server lines received in response against the
template responses. 
</p>
</section>
<section name='Using MPT'>
<subsection name='Host System'>
<p>
MPT is a lightweight, flexible framework which is capable of being used
in a variety of ways. <code>HostSystem</code> is pivotal, defining the 
interface between the framework and the server system under test.
</p>
<ul>
<li>
The <code>ExternalHostSystem</code> implementation connects to a port on a server. 
This is typically used to test a complete running server (including the sockets).
<a href='../antlib'>MPT AntLib</a> provides an
<a href='http://ant.apache.org' rel='tag'>Ant</a> task suitable for this use case.
</li>
<li>
When performing in-JVM testing (without a live server socket) a custom implementation
must be created connecting the framework to the components under test. This use case
is typically developed as a <a href='http://www.junit.org'>JUnit</a> test case.
</li>
</ul>
</subsection>
<subsection name='With JUnit'>
<p>
In-JVM JUnit testing is a typical use case. The framework provides
abstract superclasses which setup up appropriate fixtures. 
</p>
</subsection>
</section>
<section name="Script Features">
<subsection name='Basic Syntax'>
<p>
MPT scripts are line based plain text files. The initial letter of each line determines it's type:
</p>
<table>
<tr>
    <td><strong>Line Prefix</strong></td> <td><strong>Description</strong></td>
</tr> 
<tr>
    <td>#</td> 
    <td>A comment: the rest of the line will be ignored</td> 
</tr>
<tr>
    <td>C: </td> 
    <td>A client request: the rest of the line will be sent to the server</td> 
</tr>
<tr>
    <td>S: </td> 
    <td>A server response: the framework will read one line of response from the server, 
    and compare it to the rest of the line (see 
    <a href='#Regex Matching Of Server Responses'>regex matching</a>)</td> 
</tr>
</table>
<p>
Example:
</p>
<source><pre>
#
# This script is a basic SMTP HELO.
# 
S: 220 localhost. SMTP Server \(JAMES SMTP Server .*
C: HELO example.org
S: 250 localhost. Hello example.org .*
C: QUIT
S: 221 2.0.0 localhost. Service closing transmission channel
</pre></source>
</subsection>
<subsection name='Regex Matching Of Server Responses'>
<p>
The server responses in the script support regex matching. 
<a href='http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.4.2/docs/api/java/util/regex/Pattern.html'>Java Pattern</a>
is used for the regex comparison and so the syntax is identical. 
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name='Variable Substitution'>
<p>
Variables of form <code>${<em>variable-name</em>}</code> may be substituted by values
passed into the script builder before interpretation.
</p>
</subsection>
</section>
</body>
</document>