<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
  or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
  distributed with this work for additional information
  regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
  to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
  "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
  with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
  software distributed under the License is distributed on an
  "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
  KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
  specific language governing permissions and limitations
  under the License.    
-->
<document>

  <properties>
    <title>Contributors How To</title>
    <author email="site-dev@james.apache.org">James Project Web Team</author>
  </properties>

  <body>

    <section name="Introduction">
      <p>
        James is a project that lives from the contributions of its community.<br/>
        <b>Anyone can contribute.</b>
        <br />
        That's right, we always want to hear from people with
        contributions to the code,
        the documentation, the website, and bug reports.
        <br />
        The rest of this document outlines the way to go about these to
        maximum effect.
        <br />
      </p>
      <p>
        To keep you informed on James issues, subscribe to the relevant 
        <a href="https://james.apache.org/mail.html">mailing lists</a>
        <br />
      </p>
    </section>

    <section name="Be involved in the community">
      <p>
        An easy start is to be involved in the community.<br/>
        Share your experiences with James, your needs, your enhancements proposition via the
        <a href="https://james.apache.org/mail.html">mailing lists</a>, on <a href="https://gitter.im/apache/james-project">
        gitter</a>, or on our <a href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/JAMES">Bug Tracker</a>.<br/>

        Don't hesitate to write articles and blog posts. Use your preferred media to spread the love!
      </p>
    </section>

    <section name="Reporting Bugs">
      <p>
        Many improvements come as a direct result of bug reports.
        <br />
        To report a bug, please use the appropriate Bug Tracker JIRA link according
        to the project you want to address:
        <br />
        <a href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/JAMES">Server</a>
        <br />
        <a href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/MAILET">Mailet</a>
        <br />
        <a href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/MAILBOX">Mailbox</a>
        <br />
        <a href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/PROTOCOLS">Protocols</a>
        <br />
        <a href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/MPT">MPT</a>
        <br />
        <a href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/MIME4J">Mime4j</a>
        <br />
        <a href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/JSIEVE">jSieve</a>
        <br />
        <a href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/JSPF">jSPF</a>
        <br />
        <a href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/JDKIM">jDKIM</a>
        <br />
        Once you are logged on the appropriate JIRA page, 
        click on the red Create button, then complete the 
        different fields as accurately as possible, so that 
        any user can reproduce the reported bug. 
        Also note that all your information must be readable 
        (use markdown).
        <br />
        Then, you have to click on Create to submit your bug.
      </p>

      <subsection name="Reporting security vulnerabilities">
        <a class="comm" alt="Security" href="http://www.apache.org/security/">Security</a>: Vulnerabilities should be announced to the Apache Security team.<br/>
        PMCs will be notified about them, and will work hard to propose fixes as fast as possible.<br/>
        Specific details about security in James can be found <a class="comm" alt="security in James" href="http://james.apache.org/server/feature-security.html">here</a>.

      </subsection>
    </section>

    <section name="Documentation">
      <p>Documentation is an easy way to get on board!

        Check out the <a class="comm" alt="Documentation" href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/issues/?jql=project%20%3D%20JAMES%20AND%20resolution%20%3D%20Unresolved%20AND%20labels%20%3D%20documentation%20ORDER%20BY%20priority%20DESC%2C%20updated%20DESC">~documentation</a> label on JIRA to get some ideas.<br/>
        Report on JIRA the typo you spots, the information you miss, and any improvement you can think to.<br/>
        The next step is to contribute the documentation changes via <a class="comm" alt="The website on github"  href="https://github.com/apache/james-project/tree/master/src/site/xdoc">Git</a>.
      </p>
      <p>
        To edit an existing document try to edit the xml version in <code>src/site/xdoc</code>
        (check it out from GIT) and if you can, submit a patch as for Code Patches.
      </p>
      <p>
        If you want to contribute new files please try to use the markdown format as
        shown in <code>src/site/markdown</code>.
      </p>
      <p>
        If this means nothing to you please try to contribute HTML or plain
        text documents without any styling, so that we can get at the words
        and easily convert them into the right format.
      </p>
      <p>
        If all this seems like unnecessary nonsense, send us whatever you
        like, we'd still be happy to receive good documentation.
      </p>
      <p>
        Each of the Apache James projects has its own documentation
        maintained with the automated build. Once a build is done,
        the documentation can be further committed in the
        <a href="https://git-wip-us.apache.org/repos/asf/james-site.git">site module</a>
        which will be automatically published via gitpubsub
        to <a href="http://james.apache.org">Apache James web site</a>.
      </p>
      <p>
        Further to this documentation, the <a href="http://wiki.apache.org/james/">Apache James wiki</a>
        is available to any and is useful to share any useful documentation.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section name="Idea or design proposals">
      <p>People can submit ideas, features or design changes proposals by discussing it through the
        <a href="https://james.apache.org/mail.html">mailing lists</a>.</p>

      <p>Structuring design changes are tracked by <a href="https://github.com/joelparkerhenderson/architecture-decision-record">ADRs</a>
        (Architecture Decision Records). A discussion on the mailing list getting a consensus of the community can be the object
        of the writing of an ADR to confirm the change agreed upon. The Project Member Committee will take care of maintaining such
        records but anyone should feel free to help on such a task by proposing ADRs related to his work.</p>

      <p>ADRs <b>MUST</b> be submitted under the folder `src/adr` via a pull request. The standards used for writing an ADR are
        described in the <a href="https://github.com/apache/james-project/blob/master/src/adr/0001-record-architecture-decisions.md">first ADR</a>
        written for the Apache James project.</p>

      <p>The number of the ADR should be incremental. If another ADR gets merged concurrently, the committer is responsible for
        updating its number accordingly.</p>

      <p>When the ADR reaches a consensus within the community and is accepted, it can be merged and goes into effect.</p>

      <p>An ADR can't be removed after being accepted and merged. However, a new ADR can supersede a previous one. This is so
        we are able to keep track on all the decisions being made regarding the project.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="How to contribute to some code?">
      <p>We encourage discussions prior code contributions on the <a href="https://james.apache.org/mail.html">mailing lists</a>. For significant design
        changes the writing of <b>ADRs</b> is encouraged.</p>

      Your code contribution <b>MUST</b> be backed by a <a href="_reporting_bugs">JIRA ticket</a>.
      <p>
        Clone the source code of the project from its
        <a href="git://git.apache.org/james-project.git">apache git repository</a>
        or its <a href="https://github.com/apache/james-project">GitHub</a>
        <br />
        Create your branch and name it with the JIRA ticket number.<br />
        Create a Pull Request with your branch name and prefix its different commits with the same name.
        <br />
      </p>

      <p>Alternatively you can create a patch as <a href="#Code_Patches">outlined below</a>, and attach it to the JIRA ticket.</p>
      <p>A valid commit comment might be:</p>

        <pre><code>JAMES-2285 My awesome commit title

Here is some more details about what my commit does, and the rationals of the choice I took.</code></pre>

      <subsection name="Contribution proposals">
        <p>
        We reference some easy tasks to start with :
        <a class="comm" alt="Newbie tasks" href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/issues/?jql=project%20%3D%20JAMES%20AND%20resolution%20%3D%20Unresolved%20AND%20labels%20%3D%20newbie%20ORDER%20BY%20priority%20DESC%2C%20updated%20DESC">~newbie</a>
        <br/> We have a collection of minor fixes awaiting contributions:
        <a class="comm" alt="Easy fixes" href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/issues/?jql=project%20%3D%20JAMES%20AND%20resolution%20%3D%20Unresolved%20AND%20labels%20%3D%20easyfix%20ORDER%20BY%20priority%20DESC%2C%20updated%20DESC">~easyfix</a>
        <br/> Challenge yourself with some cool features we thought to:
        <a class="comm" alt="Cool features" href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/issues/?jql=project%20%3D%20JAMES%20AND%20resolution%20%3D%20Unresolved%20AND%20labels%20%3D%20feature%20ORDER%20BY%20priority%20DESC%2C%20updated%20DESC">~feature</a>
        <br/>Additional ideas are more than welcome. Don't hesitate to discuss that with us!
        </p>
      </subsection>
    </section>

    <section name="Coding Standards">
      <p>
        While we are glad to accept contributions to documentation
        from anyone, in almost any format, because its much better than none,
        please consider these guidelines to help us to assimilate your contribution.
      </p>
      <p>
        Submissions to the James project must follow the coding conventions outlined in the
        <a href="https://github.com/apache/james-project/blob/master/checkstyle.xml">checkstyle document</a>, which runs
        upon <code>mvn compile</code> and all phases which depend on <code>compile</code>. Not respecting it will halt the build, and means
        your contribution would not be acceptable.
      </p>
      <p>
        <strong>Developers who commit code that does not follow
          the coding conventions outlined in this document will be
          responsible for fixing their own code.
        </strong>
      </p>
      <p>
        1. Four spaces.<strong>NO tabs</strong>. Period. <br/>
        The James mailing list receives commit messages that
        are almost impossible to read if tabs are used.
      </p>
      <p>
        In Emacs-speak, this translates to the following command:

        (setq-default tab-width 4 indent-tabs-mode nil)
      </p>
      <p>
        2. Use Unix linefeeds for all .java source code files. Only
        platform-specific files (e.g. .bat files for Windows) should
        contain non-Unix linefeeds.
      </p>
      <p>3. Javadoc <strong>MUST</strong>
        exist on all API methods. Contributing
        a missing javadoc for any method, class, variable, etc., will
        be GREATLY appreciated as this will help to improve the James project.
      </p>
      <p>4. The standard Apache license header <strong>MUST</strong> be placed at the top of every file.</p>
      <p>5. Your change set <strong>MUST</strong> be covered by tests. We also strongly appreciate integration tests.</p>
      <p>
        6. <strong>pom.xml</strong>

        <br/>
        We also require the following best practice regarding maven:
        <ul>
          <li>Define your dependency versions in james-project pom.xml. This structurally ensures all projects get the
            same version, and that there is no version clashes.</li>
          <li>Don't use <i>org.apache.james</i> groupId for your dependencies. Use <i>${james.groupId}</i>.
            If not, you break the policies for automatic sorting, as well as make it more ambiguous.</li>
          <li>You should be ordering your dependencies. The sort order is:
            <ul>
              <ol>If the project is part of org.james.apache groupId? Internal dependencies goes first.</ol>
              <ol>Then we order by groupId</ol>
              <ol>Then we order by artifactId</ol>
              <ol>Then we order by type. <i>test-jar</i> goes last.</ol>
            </ul>
            Proper ordering is enforced by the project build. The build will fail in case violations are detected</li>
          <li>POM files, as well as sections ordering should follows the <a href="http://maven.apache.org/ref/3.0.3/maven-model/maven.html">Maven Model</a></li>
        </ul>

        You can quickly check the status of your pom files using:
        <pre>
          <code>mvn validate</code>
        </pre>
        You can ask the build to reorder pom files according to the rules using the <code>sortPom</code> profile:
        <pre>
          <code>mvn validate -PsortPom</code>
        </pre>
        <p>Make sure you properly review all changes made by the automatic rewriting as XML processing tools are liberal
        with whitespace.</p>
        <p>You should also split multiple attributes each on a new line.</p>
      </p>
      <p>
        <strong>Eclipse IDE</strong>
        <br />
        Eclipse users can import those two files to enfore the code
        formating :
        <a href="downloads/formatting.xml">formatting.xml</a>
        and
        <a href="downloads/codetemplates.xml">codetemplates.xml</a>
        .
      </p>
    </section>

    <section name="Code Patches">
      <p>While we definitely prefer receiving contributions under the form of GitHub pull requests,
        in order to still be vendor neutral on the contribution process, we do accept submission of patches, in a process described
        below.
      </p>
      <p>
        Patches should be attached to the corresponding JIRA issue.
        <br />
        <b>Always</b>
        use diff -u to generate patches, so we can apply them using
        'patch'.
        <br />

        <br />
        Make sure the patch only contains what is intended, your
        checkout could be outdated.
        <br />
        Make sure it conforms to the code standards, otherwise it may be ignored. It is OK to make a
        single patch covering several
        files, but please only one issue at a time.
        <br />
        Briefly outline the reason for your patch,
        the solution your patch implements, why a patch is
        needed and why your code will solve the problem. Note any bug numbers your
        patch addresses.
        <br />
      </p>

      <p>
        The reason for these rules is so that committers can easily see
        what you are trying to achieve,
        it is their responsibility to manage the code and review submissions,
        if you make it easy for them to see what you are doing your
        patch is more likely to
        be committed quickly.
        <br />
      </p>
    </section>

  </body>

</document>
