<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <author email="site-dev@james.apache.org">JAMES Project Web Team</author>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <section name="What is it?">
      <p>The Apache JAMES Project delivers a rich set of open source solutions, written in Java, related to internet mail and news.</p>
      <p>JAMES is organized into subprojects with JAMES Server and the Mailet API as their core.</p> 
      <p>Apache JAMEs is a project of The Apache Software Foundation (ASF) which encourages a collaborative, consensus-based development process under an open software license.</p>
      <p>The ASF maintains other Java projects which may also be of interest. These are detailed on the ASF Projects page.</p>
      <p>We recommended that users of JAMES products subscribe to the JAMES users mailing list.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="news">
    <div id="apacheconspacer">
    <div id="apacheconbox">
    <!--
    <a href="http://www.asia.apachecon.com/" target="_top"><img src="http://www.apache.org/ads/ApacheCon/234x60-2006-asia.gif" alt="ApacheCon Asia 2006" style="margin: 3px;" border="0" height="60" width="236" /></a>
    <br />
    -->
    <a href="http://www.us.apachecon.com/" target="_top"><img src="http://www.apache.org/ads/ApacheCon/234x60-2006-us.gif" alt="ApacheCon US 2006" style="margin: 3px;" border="0" height="60" width="236" /></a>
    </div></div>
    <subsection name="2006">
     <h4>JAMES Server 2.3.0 RC3 Released</h4>
     <p>James PMC is proud to announce the <a href="http://people.apache.org/dist/james/server/">availability</a> of the third, and hopefully last, release candidate of JAMES Server 2.3.0. More informations on what's new can be found in the <a href="/server/changelog.html">changelog</a>.</p>
     <p>New development roadmaps are being discussed right now, so stay tuned for 2.3.0 final and for the following news. - Sep/2006</p>
     <h4>JAMES Products website revamped</h4>
     <p>We just finished a major update of james products to be able to publish each product specific site under this new website structure  - Aug/2006</p>
     <h4>JAMES Server 2.3.0 on the way</h4>
     <p>After a long time of development we have released the first <a href="http://people.apache.org/dist/james/server/">release candidate</a> of JAMES Server 2.3.0. After a period of user testing version 2.3.0 will be released. - Jul/2006</p>
     <h4>New project JAMES jSPF</h4>
     <p>JAMES PMC is happy to announce that we are working on a Java implementation of the SPF specification. The first <a href="http://people.apache.org/dist/james/jspf/">betas</a> are already available for download. - Jul/2006</p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection name="2005">
     <h4>JAMES PMC react to the closure of Apache Avalon.</h4>
      <p>JAMES PMC would like to reassure all of our users that JAMES Server is alive and well. All of the James team have kept abreast of the Avalon developments culminating in the closure of the Avalon project and dispersal of its codebase. We are are keen to stress that this has little impact on our ability to support and develop Server in both the short and long terms.<br/>Over the coming months we will be finalising and publishing a road map for JAMES Server which will address all of the specific concerns raised by Avalon's closure, but rest assured JAMES Server' future is safe, and we have enthusiasm and plans aplenty.<br/> In the meantime we would like to extend our best wishes to all our friends from Avalon, here's luck with your future projects guys!<br/> If you are at all concerned please subscribe to the server-user mailing list and raise your points there. - 05/Jan/2005</p>

      <h4>JAMES product sources have moved to "Subversion"</h4>
      <p>Subversion is a version control system like CVS, but it has advantages over CVS for Apache Software Foundation (ASF) projects.<br/> In common with all other ASF projects we have reviewed our use of CVS and migrated our code to Subversion.<br/>
Have a look at this <a href="FAQ.html#17">FAQ</a> for further details. - 05/Jan/2005</p>
      <p/>
      </subsection>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
