<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
  or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
  distributed with this work for additional information
  regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
  to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
  "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
  with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
  software distributed under the License is distributed on an
  "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
  KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
  specific language governing permissions and limitations
  under the License.    
-->
<document>

 <properties>
  <title>James 2.3 - Mailet API</title>
 </properties>

<body>
<section name="Mailet API">
<p>The Mailet API is a simple API used to build mail processing applications.  James is a Mailet 
container, allowing administrators to deploy Mailets (both custom and pre-made) to carry out a 
variety of complex mail processing tasks.  In the default configuration James uses Mailets to carry 
out a number of tasks that are carried out deep in the source code of other mail servers (i.e. list 
processing, remote and local delivery).</p>
<p>
As it stands today, the Mailet API defines interfaces for both Matchers and Mailets.</p>
<p>Matchers, as their name would suggest, match mail messages against certain conditions.  They 
return some subset (possibly the entire set) of the original recipients of the message if there 
is a match.  An inherent part of the Matcher contract is that a Matcher should not induce any changes
in a message under evaluation.</p>
<p>Mailets are responsible for actually processing the message.  They may alter the message in any fashion,
or pass the message to an external API or component.  This can include delivering a message to its destination 
repository or SMTP server.</p>
<p>The Mailet API is currently in its second revision.  Although, the Mailet API is expected to undergo substantial changes in the near future, it is our aim that existing Mailets that abided purely by the prior Mailet API interfaces will continue to run with the revised specification.</p>
<p>The Javadoc for the Mailet API can be found <a href="apidocs/index.html">here</a>.</p>
<p>James bundles a number of Matchers and Mailets in its distribution.  Descriptions of provided matchers 
can be found <a href="provided_matchers_2_3.html">here</a>, while descriptions of provided mailets can be found 
<a href="provided_mailets_2_3.html">here</a>.</p>
</section>
</body>
</document>
