<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
  or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
  distributed with this work for additional information
  regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
  to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
  "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
  with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
  software distributed under the License is distributed on an
  "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
  KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
  specific language governing permissions and limitations
  under the License.    
-->
<document>
 <properties>
  <title>James 2.3 - Creating Mailing Lists</title>
 </properties>
<body>

<section name="How To Create Mailing Lists">
<p>One of the frequent questions on the James-User Mailing List is how
to create a mailing list. This document explains one way of using the
currently supplied Matchers and Mailets in James v2.3.</p>

<p>Basically, the process requires creating two &lt;mailet&gt; entries
and a repository.  The first mailet handles list commands (currently
only <i>list-name</i>-on and <i>list-name</i>-off).  The second mailet
handles list messages.  The repository will hold the e-mail addresses
of list subscribers.</p>

<p>The mailets go into the processor chain (e.g., at the top of the
<i>transport</i> processor), the repository goes into the
&lt;users-store&gt; block.</p>

<subsection name="Setting up the Mailets">

<p>You need to setup two mailets.</p>

<p>The first mailet that you need to setup is an instance of the <a
href="provided_mailets_2_3.html#AvalonListservManager">Avalon Listserv
Manager</a> mailet.  This will handle subscribing and unsubscribing.
[Note: the current code does not support confirmed opt-in, just basic
commands.]  The <a
href="provided_matchers_2_3.html#CommandForListserv">CommandForListserv</a>
matcher is used to invoke match messages containing commands for the
mailing list.</p>

<p>The second mailet is an instance of the <a
href="provided_mailets_2_3.html#AvalonListserv">Avalon Listserv</a>
mailet.  That mailet actually receives messages for the list and
causes them to be distributed.  The <a
href="provided_matchers_2_3.html#RecipientIs">RecipientIs</a> matcher
is used to match messages intended for the mailing list.</p>

<p>The following illustrates the two &lt;mailet&gt; elements that need to be added:</p>

<source>
  &lt;mailet match="CommandForListserv=<i>list-name</i>@<i>domain</i>"
          class="AvalonListservManager"&gt;
    &lt;repositoryName&gt;<i>list-name</i>&lt;/repositoryName&gt;
  &lt;/mailet&gt;

  &lt;mailet match="RecipientIs=<i>list-name</i>@<i>domain</i>" class="AvalonListserv"&gt;
    &lt;repositoryName&gt;<i>list-name</i>&lt;/repositoryName&gt;
    ... list options ...
  &lt;/mailet&gt;
</source>

</subsection>

<subsection name="Setting up the Repository">

<p>The mailing list mailets need a repository within which to store
the subscriber list.  There is a separate repository for each mailing
list, and is completely independent of the user repository used by
James to manage e-mail accounts.  This is configured in the
&lt;users-store&gt; block of config.xml.</p>

<p>The following illustrates a database-backed repository using JDBC
with the ListUsersJdbcRepository class.  Notice that there will be a
single table, <i>lists</i>, created in the db://maildb resource
defined elsewhere.  There are currently two columns: the list name and
the list subscriber.</p>

<source>
  &lt;repository name="<i>list-name</i>"
                 class="org.apache.james.userrepository.ListUsersJdbcRepository"
                 destinationURL="db://maildb/lists/<i>list-name</i>"&gt;
    &lt;sqlFile&gt;file://conf/sqlResources.xml&lt;/sqlFile&gt;
  &lt;/repository&gt;
</source>

<p>The following illustrates a file-system repository using the
UsersFileRepository class. [Note: the destination URL is a child
element when configuring a file-system repository, and an attribute
when configuring a database-backed repository.  This inconsistency
will be addressed in a future version of James.]</p>

<source>
  &lt;repository name="<i>list-name</i>"
                 class="org.apache.james.userrepository.UsersFileRepository"&gt;
    &lt;destination URL="file://var/lists/<i>list-name</i>/" /&gt; 
  &lt;/repository&gt;
</source>

</subsection>
</section>
</body>
</document>
